<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Liberty of conscience asserted, or, A looking-glass for persecutors being a plain deduction from scripture-history of the original grounds &amp; pretences for persecution : the methods taken to put the same in execution : together with the sad consequences thereof, or, the reward that attends persecuting-spirits.</title>
            <author>Care, Henry, 1646-1688.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 162 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33935</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C528</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31288</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11875176</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11875176</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41342</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33935)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41342)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 997:14, 1249:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Liberty of conscience asserted, or, A looking-glass for persecutors being a plain deduction from scripture-history of the original grounds &amp; pretences for persecution : the methods taken to put the same in execution : together with the sad consequences thereof, or, the reward that attends persecuting-spirits.</title>
                  <author>Care, Henry, 1646-1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by R. Janaway ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A preface to the reader" signed: H.C.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages stained with print show-through and loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Union Theological Seminary Library; Christ Church Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Liberty of conscience.</term>
               <term>Persecution.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41342:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Liberty of Conſcience ASSERTED, OR A Looking-Glaſs FOR PERSECUTORS; Being a plain Deduction from Scripture-Hiſtory OF THE <hi>Original Grounds &amp; Pretences</hi> FOR PERSECUTION.</p>
            <p>The <hi>METHODS</hi> taken to put the ſame in Execution.</p>
            <p>Together with the ſad <hi>Conſequences</hi> thereof: Or, The <hi>Reward</hi> that attends <hi>Perſecuting-Spirits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed and ſold by <hi>R. Janaway</hi> in <hi>Queens-Head-Alley,</hi> in <hi>Pater-Noſter-Row,</hi> 1687.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:41342:2"/>
            <head>A PREFACE to the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>PErſecution for Religion is almoſt as old as the <hi>World;</hi> The <hi>firſt Murther</hi> under the Sun, being committed on that account, when <hi>Cain</hi> aſſaſſinated his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Brother <hi>Abel,</hi> meerly becauſe he worſhip'd God <hi>better</hi> than himſelf; and ever ſince the Enmity has continued: And when it will pleaſe <hi>Almighty Wiſdom</hi> to put a final Period to ſuch Practices throughout the World, we are not able to determin.</p>
            <p>But ſince <hi>merciful Providence</hi> has vouchſafed ſo to diſpoſe the Royal Heart of our Gracious <hi>Sovereign,</hi> as to give a <hi>Stop,</hi> and we hope, <hi>total Abolition</hi> thereunto, in the Land of our Nativity; and to open a Door to the <hi>Oppreſſed,</hi> that they may both peaceably worſhip their Creator, according to the beſt of their Light; and freely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate the Evils of the <hi>Perſecuting Spirit,</hi> to thoſe who lately were ſo intirely poſſeſt therewith; that even to <hi>complain</hi> of thoſe Severities we unjuſtly ſuffered, was made a <hi>new Crime.</hi> It muſt certainly be <hi>our Duty</hi> to improve this Opportunity as far as we can, to the common Intereſt of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>Not in the leaſt to <hi>reflect</hi> upon, or upbraid any for paſt Miſcarriages; much leſs to ſtir up any <hi>Heart-burnings,</hi> or motions towards <hi>Revenge</hi> or <hi>Animoſities;</hi> but only to convince ſuch as have had any hand in <hi>rigid Perſecutions</hi> againſt their <hi>Neighbors,</hi> meerly on the Score of a <hi>Conſcientious Diſſent</hi> in Matters of Religion, of the Evil of ſuch Proceedings; and to caution all others for the future, againſt the like Violences.</p>
            <p>To advance theſe good and wholſom Ends, is the deſign and purport of the <hi>follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Treatiſe;</hi> which in a plain <hi>familiar Stile,</hi> endeavors to give the World a true Proſpect (altogether deduced from Holy Writ) of the <hi>Original Source,</hi> and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral grounds from whence <hi>Perſecution</hi> has in all Ages aroſe, and been propagated a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Men. The <hi>Means, Methods,</hi> and <hi>Pretences,</hi> whereby the ſame has been carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on and palliated: As likewiſe the ſad <hi>Conſequences</hi> thereof in the heavy Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, righteouſly inflicted by Almighty God, (even in this World,) on thoſe that have been guilty of ſuch Out-rages.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, As the natural Man views his own Viſſage and all the Lineaments of his Countenance in a common Glaſs, ſo every Murthering <hi>Cain,</hi> or Oppreſſive <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> or Envious <hi>Haman,</hi> or Blaſphemous <hi>Rabſhekah,</hi> or Raging <hi>Samballat,</hi> or Bloody <hi>Herod,</hi> or Treacherous <hi>Judas,</hi> and all and every their Succeſſors, may in this Portraiture, (drawn to the Life by the Holy Ghoſt, in the <hi>Inſpired Writings,</hi>) behold repreſented the true Character of <hi>themſelves,</hi> their Motives, Deſigns, Words, Actings, and (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſincere Repentance,) of their final <hi>Doom</hi> and <hi>Deſtruction</hi> too.</p>
            <p>That the <hi>divine Bleſſing</hi> may ſo far accompany this <hi>Mean,</hi> but well intended <hi>Work,</hi> as to render it inſtrumental to bring ſome that have been Concern'd in this Kind, to an hearty Acknowledgment of their Crimes: And to make Perſecution for Conſcience, an <hi>Abhorrence</hi> to all that profeſs to call on the Name of the Bleſſed <hi>JESUS,</hi> who is both the Prince of <hi>Peace,</hi> the Fountain of <hi>Love,</hi> the grand Examplar of <hi>Meekneſs,</hi> and Author of all <hi>Conſolation,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Shall be the Prayer of the Publiſher,</hi> H. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41342:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>Whatſoever things were written aforetime, were written for our Learning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Rom. XV. 3, 4.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe things hapned to them for Examples: and they were written for our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition, upon whom the ends of the World are come, <bibl>
                        <hi>1 Cor. X. 11.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Holy Scriptures being written and continued for the Learning and Admonition of thoſe who ſhould live in <hi>future Ages;</hi> eſpecially, of thoſe upon whom <hi>the ends of the World are come.</hi> It doth highly concern every one (who believes the things therein written, to be Truth and Verity,) to be inſtructing themſelves in the Matters which theſe <hi>divine Records</hi> do contain; to the end, that they may learn and be admoniſhed thereby, to follow the <hi>good Examples</hi> of Chriſt himſelf, and of the eminent Saints therein mentioned; be of ſuch a Spirit as they were of; walk, and do as they did, that it may be well with them in the latter end: And to the intent that they may take heed of being found in the Spirit and Practices of ſome others who lived in thoſe days, and were of <hi>a contrary Temper</hi> to the former, and did otherwiſe than they did; and ſo conſequently, eſcape the direful Effects, which in thoſe days fell upon ſome of theſe latter ones; and that all ſuch may be aſſured, they ſhall feel at the laſt day.</p>
            <p>One grand thing therefore written, and here and there to be found ſcattered in thoſe divine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, worthy obſervation, and to be ſeriouſly conſidered by all Men, (tho I fear, leaſt obſerved, or flightly thought on by moſt,) as that which is a Matter of no ſmall moment and concern to them; for the warning and awakening of ſome, comfort and quiet of others, Is this, <hi>viz.</hi> The great <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition</hi> between the <hi>Two Seeds</hi> of the <hi>Serpent</hi> and the <hi>Woman,</hi> the <hi>World</hi> and <hi>Chriſt;</hi> thoſe who are born after the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and thoſe who are born after the <hi>Spirit;</hi> thoſe who are yet <hi>of the World,</hi> and thoſe who are called <hi>out of the World;</hi> the <hi>wicked</hi> of the World, and the <hi>Saints</hi> of the moſt High God. No ſooner were Men born from above, and evidenced the ſame by their Works, but wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Men not yet born again, were ready to devour them; as the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith, Chap. 59.15. <hi>He who departeth from evil, maketh himſelf a prey.</hi> No ſooner depart from Evil, but the Teeth of the wicked were edged againſt them.</p>
            <p>The Evidences of which, the Scripture hath abundantly delivered down to after Ages: It teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth, not only of the Enmity, Envy, Malice, and bitterneſs which was rooted, ſeated, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominated in the Breaſts of Men, whilſt in the Fleſh, yet Children of the wicked One in thoſe Ages, againſt them who were born of the Spirit, Subjects of the King of Kings, followers of God and Chriſt, yea, againſt <hi>Holineſs</hi> it ſelf, againſt the Laws of Chriſt, and his Government; their Hearts ſaid as <hi>Pharaoh's</hi> did, <hi>Exod.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Who is the Lord, that I ſhould obey him?</hi> And as Chriſt in a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, intimates the Hearts of the <hi>Jews</hi> to be, ſaying, <hi>Luke</hi> 19. in theſe words, His Citizens hated him, and ſaid, <hi>We will not have this Man to rule over us.</hi> v. 14. <hi>Nor will we endure any of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects.</hi> But alſo of the very <hi>Methods</hi> and <hi>Ways</hi> wherein they expreſſed this Enmity and bitterneſs of Spirit that was ſo fixed in them, both by Word and Deed: Yea, moreover, the very <hi>Cauſes</hi> from whence all the former did ſpring; as alſo the <hi>ſad Effects</hi> which was like to follow, or be the reward of ſuch Spirits and Doings.</p>
            <p>The critical obſervation of all which, when well ſearched out, might be that no ſmall uſe in all Ages to all Men; for there is no <hi>New Thing under the Sun,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> Eccleſ. 1.9.</p>
            <p>Of theſe in their order: And firſt of the <hi>Evidences</hi> and <hi>Inſtances</hi> which the Scripture hath given and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oted; Of the Firſt, (to wit,) That the <hi>ſeated Enmity</hi> in the Hearts of the wicked, and their bitterneſs againſt God himſelf, Chriſt, his Followers, the Saints of God, the Laws of God, Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41342:3"/> it ſelf, and the Light thereof; the Light which did ſhine in Chriſt himſelf, the Saints and followers of Chriſt; which Enmity the Holy Ghoſt did fore-tell, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. ſhould ariſe between the Seed of the Serpent and the Seed of the Woman; and accordingly it ſoon appeared, when <hi>Cain</hi> from that Principle, ſlew his Brother <hi>Abel, Gen.</hi> 4.8. The Prophet <hi>Habakuk,</hi> in his time, noted, <hi>Chap.</hi> 1.13. That the wicked <hi>devoured the Man that was more righteous than he.</hi> The Apoſtle alſo aſſerts, that in thoſe days alſo, 'twas ſo in the general, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.29. As he who was born <hi>after the Fleſh, perſecuted him who was born after the Spirit;</hi> ſo (ſaith he there,) it is now, that is, in thoſe days: By which they then did evidence the higheſt Heart-Enmity imaginable.</p>
            <p>And this Heart-Enmity, the Holy Ghoſt hath throughout the Old and New Teſtament frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in eſpecial manner obſerved. No ſooner had the Enemies of the <hi>Jews,</hi> in <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> days, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 2. received Intelligence, that <hi>Nehemiah</hi> was come with Authority to <hi>build the Walls of Jeruſalem,</hi> v. 8.9. But 'tis ſaid, <hi>v.</hi> 10. That <hi>it grieved them exceedingly, that there was come a Man to ſeek the wellfare of the Children of</hi> Iſrael; their envious Hearts here boiled within them of it; when there was one good Prophet in <hi>Iſrael, Micaiah</hi> by name, wicked <hi>Ahab</hi> ſaid of him, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 22.8. <hi>I hate him.</hi> Such was his ſeated Enmity againſt him there, that he could not, in that time, forbear openly to declare it upon the very naming of him. The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> alſo teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that in his time it was ſo; <hi>The wicked in wrath,</hi> or (as the Margent hath it,) <hi>with un inteſtine hatred,</hi> (ſaith he,) <hi>hateth me,</hi> Pſ. 55. v. 3. And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 64.4. He complains of the numerouſneſs of theſe two, in theſe words, <hi>They who hate me without a Cauſe, are more than the Hairs of my Head.</hi> Of which Enmity alſo, the Prophet <hi>Amos</hi> takes notice in the general in his days; <hi>They hate</hi> (ſaith he,) <hi>rebuke in the Gate, and they abhor him who ſpeaketh uprightly,</hi> Amos 5.10. They there could not endure <hi>Verbal Rebuke,</hi> nor the convincing Life of an upright Man, their Hearts abhorred them both. So afterwards, in New Teſtament days, they teſtified their fixed Enmity, Hatred and Rancour, which was ſeated in their Minds againſt Chriſt himſelf, and againſt all who did own <hi>Him</hi> or his Laws: As Chriſt in the Parable before mentioned, <hi>Luke</hi> 19. did hint that the <hi>Jews</hi> did, when he there ſaid of the Noble Man, <hi>v.</hi> 14. <hi>His Citizens hated him;</hi> and down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly tells him by their Meſſenger there, <hi>We will not have this Man to reign over us;</hi> there they declared their Heart-hatred againſt him and his Government in the general, and conſequently a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all who owned him, and ſubmitted themſelves to his Laws; they hated the Light which ſhone in him, them, and it; as Chriſt himſelf expreſly ſaid, <hi>John</hi> 3. That <hi>they hated the Light;</hi> v. 19.20. <hi>Light is come into the World,</hi> (ſaith he there,) <hi>and Men love darkneſs rather than light, becauſe their deeds were evil;</hi> for every one that doth evil <hi>hateth the Light,</hi> leſt his Deeds ſhould be diſcovered: And this Chriſt told his unbelieving Brethren, <hi>John</hi> 7.7. <hi>The World cannot hate you, but me it hateth, becauſe I teſtifie of it.</hi> Nay, their hatred of Chriſt was ſo evident and well known, that <hi>Pilate</hi> himſelf had taken notice of it, <hi>Mark</hi> 15.13. 'tis ſaid of him there, That he knew, that the Chief Prieſts had delivered Chriſt to be Crucified <hi>for Envy.</hi> Of which the Hearts of the unbelieving <hi>Jews</hi> were full; which alſo Chriſt did beforehand inform his Diſciples of, that they might be prepared to meet with the Effects thereof, <hi>John</hi> 15.18, 19. in theſe words, If <hi>the World hate you, ye know that it hated me firſt, before it hated you,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I have choſen you out of the World, therefore the World hateth you;</hi> here they hated Chriſt and others alſo, <hi>becauſe they followed him, and bore his image;</hi> yea, further, ſaith Chriſt there, <hi>v.</hi> 24. of the ſame Chap. <hi>Now have they both ſeen, and hated both me and my Father:</hi> Again, <hi>John</hi> 17.14. he ſaid of his Diſcipes, <hi>The world hath hated them, becauſe they are not of the world,</hi> &amp;c. Thus did Chriſt, again, and again, inculcate this, which afterwards they found true, as the Scripture alſo hath noted, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.17, 18. 'tis ſaid, That the High Prieſts, and thoſe who were with him, roſe up, and were filled with Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation or Envy, and laid their hands on the Apoſtles. The like Spirit the <hi>Jews</hi> diſcovered, <hi>Act.</hi> 13. when they there ſaw the multitude, v. 45. <hi>They were filled with Envy, and ſpake againſt thoſe things which were ſpoken by</hi> Paul; their Hearts here were full of Envy and Hatred both againſt the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:41342:3"/> and their Doctrin: Again, <hi>Act.</hi> 17. 'tis ſaid, <hi>That the</hi> Jews, <hi>who believed not, being moved with Envy, took unto them certain lew'd Fellows of the baſer ſort, and made an uprore,</hi> v. 5. And <hi>Paul</hi> doth acknowledge of himſelf, <hi>Acts</hi> 26. <hi>That he, when he was yet an unbeliever, was alſo exceeding mad againſt the followers of Chriſt,</hi> v. 9. <hi>I verily thought with my ſelf, that I ought to do many things contrary to the Name of Jeſus;</hi> and in <hi>v.</hi> 11. <hi>Being exceeding mad againſt them, I perſecuted them to ſtrange Cities.</hi> And herein was verified that which Chriſt had ſaid, <hi>John</hi> 16.1.2, 3. <hi>That ſome ſhould think that they did God good ſervice, in killing his Followers.</hi> So far did <hi>Pauls</hi> blind Zeal then tranſport him, <hi>That it filled his heart with madneſs againſt them.</hi> So far were ſome of the <hi>Jews</hi> carried in this Enmity, That when <hi>Judas</hi> repented, and told them that he <hi>had betrayed Innocent Blood,</hi> they ſay, <hi>what is that to us?</hi> (tho they rejoyced, and had given him Money to do it, <hi>Mark</hi> 14.10, 11.) and they afterwards put Chriſt to death, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.34, 35, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yea, moſt deſperately did they ſay, (when <hi>Pilate</hi> acquitted himſelf of that Innocent Blood,) <hi>His Blood be upon Us and our Children,</hi> v. 24.25. of the ſame Chap. Thus hath the Holy Ghoſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded this Enmity, that was naturally ſeated and fixed in the Hearts of the Sons of Men, and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denced by them in thoſe days.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly. As to the various <hi>Ways</hi> and <hi>Methods</hi> theſe invidious Ones walked in and took, towards and againſt the <hi>Saints,</hi> againſt Chriſt himſelf and his Followers; Or how theſe wicked Ones did in thoſe Ages of the World, expreſs this their ſeated Enmity, Hatred, and Bitterneſs againſt them; or, which way it did evidence it ſelf to be in them: The Scripture hath alſo plainly taken notice of; ſome of which were as followeth.</p>
            <p>Firſt, They were ſtudious and diligent by all means imaginable, to <hi>defame</hi> and <hi>diſgrace</hi> the Saints before Chriſt was manifeſt in the Fleſh, and afterwards to defame and diſgrace <hi>Him</hi> and his <hi>Followers,</hi> and to render their Perſons and Doctrins <hi>baſe and contemptible</hi> in the Eyes and Opinions of others, eſpecially of the <hi>Greek Ones,</hi> thereby to prevent the ſpreading of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and to ſtir up the Minds of others to be evilly affected againſt the Saints, Chriſt himſelf, and his Followers, yea, and againſt the Doctrin of the Goſpel, and Rules of Holineſs it ſelf.</p>
            <p>For the effecting of which, They <hi>ſpeak evil</hi> of them in the general, and in their ordinary Diſcourſe, and ſometimes, by charging and accuſing them in particular, with great Crimes and Enormities which they could not prove: And firſt in the general in their ordinary Diſcourſe, as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.19, 20. of the wicked there, <hi>Their Tongue frameth deceit; thou ſitteſt and ſpeakeſt againſt thy Brother, thou ſlandereſt thine own Mothers Son:</hi> Again, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 64.2, 3, 4. <hi>They whet their Tongues like a Sword, bend their bow to ſhoot their Arrows, even bitter Words, that they might ſhoot in ſecret at the perfect,</hi> &amp;c. They thus endeavored to wound them in their Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and to bring them into contempt amongſt the Vulgar, who had heard their Speeches of this dealing; the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> complains before God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94.3. <hi>Lord, how long</hi> (ſaith he,) <hi>ſhall the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed triumph, ſhall they utter and ſpeak hard things.</hi> The Holy Ghoſt in the New Teſtament too, takes notice hereof, <hi>Act.</hi> 28. The <hi>Jews</hi> there acknowledged to <hi>Paul,</hi> that 'twas ordinary for them to ſpeak againſt the followers of Chriſt, in theſe words, <hi>v.</hi> 22. <hi>This Sect we know, is every where ſpoken againſt;</hi> they were reproached as a Sect, and their Doctrin derided in the common Diſcourſe among the unbelieving <hi>Jews,</hi> every where, in thoſe days.</p>
            <p>What kind of Speeches theſe were, (as to many of them) the Sceipture doth alſo in particular record, as in that of <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.18, 19. <hi>John came neither eating or drinking, and they ſaid he hath a Devil. The Son of Man came eating and drinking, and they ſaid, behold, a Man gluttenous, a Wine-bibber, a friend of Publicans and Sinners.</hi> Eat or not eat, they ſtill ſpeak evil of them, and all to prevent others from having any good Opinion of them or their Doctrins; ſo, when they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived that the People began to be amazed at what Chriſt had done, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.23. The Phariſees hearing thereof, <hi>v.</hi> 24. ſaid of Chriſt, <hi>This Fellow doth not caſt out Devils, but by</hi> Beelzebub <hi>the Prince of Devils;</hi> this they did, that none ſhould value him upon the account of the Miracles he
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41342:4"/> did: Again, The Phariſees, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27. gave him no better a Title than the Deceiver; <hi>We remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> (ſaid they there,) <hi>v.</hi> 62 <hi>&amp;</hi> 63. <hi>That the Deceiver ſaid, whilſt he was yet alive,</hi> &amp;c. So <hi>John</hi> the 7th, when ſome had ſaid, <hi>He is a good Man,</hi> v. 12. others ſaid, <hi>Nay, but he deceiveth the People;</hi> yea, his own Countrymen, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. tho they there were aſtoniſhed at Chriſts Wiſdom and his mighty Works; <hi>v.</hi> 54. yet, the ſame Perſons, in the following verſes, endeavor to leſſen him, and what he ſaid and did; <hi>Is not this</hi> (ſay they,) <hi>the Carpenters Son? is not his Mother called</hi> Mary, <hi>&amp;c. And they were offended in him,</hi> v. 57. So did they uſually ſpeak contemptuouſly of him, as in <hi>Luke</hi> 23.2. <hi>We found this fellow perverting the Nation,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>John</hi> 9.29. <hi>As for this Fellow, we know not from whence he is;</hi> yea, they endeavored to inſinuate this Perſuaſion into the People, in the 16th verſe of the ſame Chap. that Chriſt was not of God; ſome of the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees there ſaid, <hi>This Man is not of God, becauſe he keepeth not the Sabbath:</hi> And further, he having cured the blind Man afterwards, in the ſame Chap. and they could not deny it; they in <hi>v.</hi> 24. ſaid, <hi>Give God the glory, this Man is a ſinner;</hi> And again, <hi>John</hi> 10.20. <hi>Many of them ſaid, he hath a Devil, he is mad, why hear ye him?</hi> In like manner, <hi>John</hi> 7, when they perceived that the Officers had Chriſt in admiration, <hi>v.</hi> 46. and had ſaid there, <hi>Never Man ſpake like this Man;</hi> the Phariſees, in the next verſes, anſwered them, ſaying, <hi>Are ye alſo deceived; have any of the Rulers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved on him; But this People who know not the Law, are accurſed:</hi> And <hi>v.</hi> 52. they ſaid unto <hi>Nichodemus, Art thou alſo of</hi> Galilee? In all thoſe Expreſſions of theirs, they did endeavor to inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate this into the Peoples Minds, that Chriſt was ſo contemptible a Perſon, and all that he did was ſo little to be regarded, that no Ruler or Phariſee, Men of any Note, did account him worthy to be believed, or had in any eſteem; and that none but ignorant and accurſed People, would value him, or any thing he did; and thereby, they hoped to engage the People to ſlight him, and his Doctrin too. After the ſame manner, did they frequently ſpeak concerning the Apoſtles and their Doctrin, to diſgrace them and it amongſt the People; <hi>Acts</hi> 13. The <hi>Jews</hi> there, had no ſooner perceived that the People began to flock together to hear the Goſpel, <hi>v.</hi> 44. <hi>But they were filled with Envy, and ſpake againſt thoſe things which were ſpoken by</hi> Paul, <hi>contradicting and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming.</hi> In the following verſes, again, <hi>Act.</hi> 19. 'tis ſaid, When he had preached the Word for ſome time, <hi>v.</hi> 8. <hi>Divers were hardned and believed not, but ſpake evil of that Way before the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude,</hi> v. 9. By which means, doubtleſs, they did ſtir up the Minds of Men againſt the Apoſtles and their Doctrins; for 'tis ſaid, <hi>Act.</hi> 14.2. <hi>That the unbelieving</hi> Jews <hi>did ſtir up the Gentiles, and made their minds evilly affected againſt the Brethren;</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 19. <hi>They perſuaded the people, and having ſtoned</hi> Paul, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And again, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.13. <hi>They there ſtirred up the People;</hi> this muſt needs be by repreſenting them as ill Men, and their Doctrin as evil, in the Ears of the People. There were certain Philoſophers, <hi>Act.</hi> 18. who (when <hi>Paul</hi> had diſputed with the <hi>Jews,</hi>) took this way too, <hi>v.</hi> 17. ſaid they of <hi>Paul</hi> there, <hi>What will this babler</hi> (or baſe Fellow) <hi>ſay?</hi> otherſome ſaid, <hi>He ſeemeth to be a ſetter forth of ſtrange gods:</hi> And again, <hi>Act.</hi> 22. Having nothing in particular to charge him with, they in <hi>v.</hi> 22. (that they might engage the Magiſtrates and People againſt him, by a loud Out cry againſt him as a Monſter,) they are ſaid there, <hi>To lift up their voices, and ſay away with ſuch a Fellow from the Earth: for it is not fit that he ſhould live.</hi> And to ſpeak evil of all ſuch who owned Chriſt, was (it ſeemeth,) a common thing among them; for <hi>Pauls</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymen ſaid to him, <hi>Act.</hi> 28.22. <hi>As concerning this Sect, we know that every where it is ſpoken againſt:</hi> And <hi>Peter</hi> alſo hints this, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16. when he adviſeth the Chriſtian there, to have a good Conſcience, he ſubjoined this, <hi>That whereas they ſpeak evil of you, as of evil doers, they may be aſhamed, who did falſly accuſe your good Converſation in Chriſt;</hi> ſo Chriſts words implies, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. when he ſaid <hi>v.</hi> 11. <hi>Bleſſed ye, when Men ſhall revile you,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and ſhall ſay all manner of evil againſt you, for my ſake.</hi> Thus the Scripture declare fully, that wicked Men did expreſs their Heart-En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity againſt the Saints, Chriſt himſelf, and his Followers, by defaming and diſgracing of them and their Doctrin; thereby to bring them into Contempt, and evil Eſteem amongſt the People, and render their Doctrin of no force.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:41342:4"/>
            <p>And 2dly, Theſe wicked Ones, Unbelievers, (that they might ſeem unto all Men to be very juſt and righteous in all that which they did, and that they did require nothing but the due execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Law</hi> upon thoſe whom they perſecuted,) did not reſt in a ſpeaking evil of the Saints in the general, as before, but proceeded further (and that without any ſenſe of Honeſty or Religion,) to render them highly Criminal, (tho moſt unjuſtly and falſly,) by accuſing and charging of them as guilty of the moſt heinous Crimes; as Enemies to Kings, Governors and Government, as Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, Traytors, Seditious, Factious, breakers of the Kings Laws, and the Law of God too; breakers of the Peace, Deceivers, Ring leaders of Hereſies, and ſuch like, which they could never prove; and this they did uſually in thoſe days, before Magiſtrates and among the People; and not only ſo, but they did uſe many Artifices to inſinuate into the Peoples Minds, and alſo into the Rulers, to perſuade them fully to believe, that thoſe Accuſed Ones were really guilty of thoſe things their Perſecutors then charged them with, and thereby both Magiſtrates and People were the eaſier drawn to aſſiſt the Perſecutors; all which, the ſame Scripture alſo hath fully noted: As in <hi>John</hi> 18. when Chriſt there had been brought by them before <hi>Pilate,</hi> and he had asked them, What Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they had againſt him, <hi>v.</hi> 29. They ſaid unto him, <hi>v.</hi> 30. <hi>If he were not a Malefactor, we would not have delivered him up to thee;</hi> No doubt, they would have been thought by <hi>Pilate</hi> and thoſe preſent, to have been ſo juſt, (tho they could prove nothing againſt Chriſt,) that they muſt believe them barely upon their confident ſaying ſo, without more ado; and that <hi>Pilate</hi> ought not to think otherwiſe, when they had brought Chriſt before him, but that he muſt be a Malefactor, and not Innocent. The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> in his days, complains, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38. in general, <hi>They</hi> (ſaith he there,) <hi>who ſeek my hurt, ſpeak miſchievous things, and imagin deceit all the day long,</hi> v. 12. And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.13. <hi>I have heard the Slanders of many,</hi> &amp;c. Particular inſtances hereof are noted throughout the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Records, as in <hi>Exod.</hi> 1. The King of <hi>Egypt</hi> there (having a mind to prevent the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> growth, and to ſuppreſs them,) <hi>v.</hi> 9. he ſuggeſts this againſt them, as if they had Rebellious and Trayterous Principles in them, <hi>v.</hi> 10. in theſe words, <hi>Come, let us deal wiſely with them, leſt they multiply, and it come to paſs that when there fall out any War, they joyn alſo unto our Enemies, and fight againſt us,</hi> &amp;c. So did that wicked King <hi>Ahab,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18. (when his own great wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, mentioned 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 16.30, 31, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> had procured the ſore Famine, propheſied of by <hi>Elijah,</hi> Chap. 17.1.) he having ſought <hi>Elijah</hi> every where to kill him, <hi>v.</hi> 10. upon ſight of him, he preſently charged him for being the Troubler of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> in theſe words, <hi>v.</hi> 17. <hi>Art thou he who troubleth</hi> Iſrael? this was a moſt unjuſt Charge, as <hi>Elijah</hi> then and there told him, in the next verſe, in theſe words, <hi>I have not troubled</hi> Iſrael; <hi>but thou and thy Fathers Houſe, in that ye have forſaken the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. The Enemies of the <hi>Jews,</hi> in <hi>Ezra's</hi> time, did ſo againſt them, in <hi>Ezra</hi> 4. They there wrote Accuſations againſt them; the Chancellor and ſome other Great Ones, wrote to the King in theſe words, <hi>v.</hi> 12. and ſo on, <hi>Be it known unto the King, That if this City be builded, and the Walls-ſet up again, then they will not pay Tole, Tribute and Cuſtom; and ſo thou ſhalt endamage the Revenues of the Kings; know that this City is a Rebellious City, and hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to Kings and Provinces, and that they have moved Seditions within the ſame of old time:</hi> Here were theſe charged to be a Rebellious, Seditious, and diſloyal People; by which ſuggeſtion, (tho never ſo falſe,) they got Authority to ſtay the Work, <hi>v.</hi> 21. In like manner, did they in <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> time, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 2. when he came with Authority from the King to rebuild <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> v. 8.9, 10. <hi>Sanballat</hi> and others having heard on't, <hi>v.</hi> 19. they ſaid to them, <hi>What is the thing that ye do? will ye rebel againſt the King?</hi> Here they preſently ſuggeſted a Deſign of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion; tho, what they were about at that time, they did by the Kings own Authority: And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, <hi>Sanballat,</hi> Chap. 6. ſent to <hi>Nehemiah</hi> a Letter, in theſe words, <hi>v.</hi> 5.6, 7. <hi>It is reported a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Heathens, and</hi> Gaſhum <hi>ſaith, thou and the</hi> Jews <hi>think to rebel; for which cauſe thou buildeſt the Wall, that thou mayſt be their King, according to theſe words; and thou haſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Prophets to preach of thee at</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>ſaying, a King in</hi> Judah; than all which, there was
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41342:5"/> nothing more untrue, as <hi>Nehemiah</hi> did tell him, <hi>v.</hi> 8. ſaid he there, <hi>There is no ſuch thing done as thou ſaid, but thou faineſt them out of thine own heart:</hi> Heinous deſperate Enmity he had in his Breſt againſt <hi>Mordicai,</hi> put him upon taking this Courſe againſt him, and againſt all the <hi>Jews,</hi> the eaſier to bring about their deſtruction; he accuſeth the <hi>Jews</hi> before the King, <hi>Heſter</hi> 3. in theſe words, <hi>v.</hi> 8. &amp; 9. <hi>There is a certain People ſcattered abroad,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and their Laws are divers from all people, neither keep they the Kings Laws; That it is not for the Kings profit to ſuffer them; Let it be written, that they may be deſtroyed;</hi> By which Suggeſtion and falſe Charge, he procured a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree to deſtroy them, in the next verſes. Thus alſo did the Preſidents and Princes in <hi>Daniels</hi> time; their Enmity was ſo great againſt <hi>Daniel, That</hi> (having on purpoſe, <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.4, 5. and following verſes, procured a Law in the matter of his God, they not being able otherwiſe to accuſe him, and prove any fault againſt him,) <hi>they go to the King,</hi> in <hi>v.</hi> 13. and charge <hi>Daniel,</hi> in theſe words, in the preſence of the King, <hi>Daniel,</hi> (ſaid they,) <hi>regardeth not thee, O King, nor the Decree which thou haſt ſigned,</hi> &amp;c. Here did they inſinuate, that he was a Contemner of the King, and of his Decrees; when as in truth it was nothing ſo, but only a due regard to the true God, on whom he was bound to call. The <hi>Jews</hi> likewiſe, who believed not in Chriſt, in his time and afterwards, trod in the ſame Steps; they charged Chriſt himſelf with ſuch Crimes. <hi>Luke</hi> 23.2. <hi>They began to accuſe him before</hi> Pilate, <hi>ſaying, We found this Fellow perverting the Nation, and forbidding to give Tribute to</hi> Caeſar, <hi>ſaying, that he himſelf is Chriſt, a King;</hi> and in <hi>v.</hi> 5. <hi>He ſtirred up the people, teaching throughout all</hi> Jury, and <hi>v.</hi> 10. <hi>The chief Prieſts and Scribes ſtood up, and vehemently accuſed him;</hi> Here this moſt holy and juſt One, came under an Accuſation of being guilty of Treaſon, Sedition, and of being notoriouſly Criminal, and was vehemently accuſed too; that they might vent their Envy and Malice againſt him, with the greateſt ſhew of Juſtice; for they were tender of their own Reputation in that, as appeared, when Chriſt had ſaid unto them, <hi>John</hi> 10.32. <hi>Many good Works I have ſhewed you,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>for which of theſe Works do you ſtone me?</hi> They in the next verſe anſwered him, in theſe words, <hi>For a good Work we ſtone thee not, but for Blaſphemy, and becauſe thou being a Man, make thy ſelf a God.</hi> They would not be thought to ſhed Innocent Blood, which made them to ſtorm at the Apoſtles afterwards; when they had preached Chriſt as the Juſt One, whom the unbelieving <hi>Jews</hi> had Crucified, <hi>Act.</hi> 5 <hi>Did not we</hi> (ſay they,) <hi>v.</hi> 28. <hi>charge you, that you ſhould not teach in this Name, and behold, ye have filled</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>with your Doctrin, and intend to bring this Mans Blood on us;</hi> tho they were really guilty on't, and doubtleſs conſcious to themſelves on't too, yet would not they have others conceive ſuch a thought of them. So dealt they with <hi>Stephen, Act.</hi> 6. when they could not reſiſt the Spirit and Wiſdom, by which he ſpake, <hi>v.</hi> 10. they then in the next verſe, charge him with ſpeaking of Blaſphemy, which alſo was notoriouſly falſe; for there the Scripture ſaith, That they ſuborned Men who ſaid ſo of him; the ſame way did the South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayers take too, <hi>Act.</hi> 16. when <hi>Paul</hi> there had caſt out the evil Spirit, <hi>v.</hi> 18. <hi>They</hi> v. 19. <hi>caught</hi> Paul <hi>and</hi> Sylas, <hi>and brought them to the Magiſtrates;</hi> and in the next verſes, they charged them, in theſe words, <hi>Theſe Men being</hi> Jews, <hi>do exceedingly trouble our City, and teach Cuſtoms which are not lawful for us to receive, neither obſerve, being</hi> Romans; all which the Magiſtrates and People preſently believing to be true, without any further enquiry, fell upon <hi>Paul,</hi> &amp;c. verſes 22, 23. So did the unbelieving <hi>Jews</hi> with <hi>Jaſon,</hi> and certain Brethren, <hi>Act.</hi> 17. when they had brought them to the Rulers, <hi>v</hi> 6. they in the ſame verſes, and <hi>v.</hi> 7. charge them as guilty of Treaſon, breach of Laws, and diſturbance of the Peace too, in theſe words, <hi>Theſe have turned the world upſide down,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>theſe do all contrary to the Decrees of</hi> Caeſar, <hi>ſaying, That there is another King</hi> Jeſus; Here did they make falſe conſtruction of their Doctrin; they preached Jeſus to be the Chriſt, a King; therefore would they force it to intend againſt <hi>Caeſar:</hi> And again, <hi>Act.</hi> 18. did they ſo with <hi>Paul;</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> there <hi>v.</hi> 12. made an <hi>Inſurrection,</hi> with one accord, againſt <hi>Paul,</hi> and brought him to the <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-ſeat;</hi> and there they charge him, in theſe words, <hi>v.</hi> 13. <hi>This Fellow perſuaded Men to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God contrary to Law;</hi> and again, <hi>In the Temple they laid hold on him,</hi> Act. 21.27, 28. <hi>They
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41342:5"/> cryed out, Men of</hi> Iſrael <hi>help, this is the Man who teacheth all Men every where, againſt the People, and the Law, and this Place, and brought</hi> Greeks <hi>into the Temple and polluted this holy place;</hi> at which the People were preſently moved, eaſily believed all the Charge; and they took <hi>Paul,</hi> v. 30. and would have <hi>killed him,</hi> as in the following verſes, altho no part of the Accuſation was true: And again, <hi>Act.</hi> 24. The High Prieſt and Elders took <hi>Tertullus</hi> an Orator, with them, <hi>v.</hi> 2. that they might charge <hi>Paul</hi> more effectually, and with more facility get the Governors Ear; and when they were there before the Governor, they, by their Orator, loaded <hi>Paul</hi> with the guilt of great Crimes, <hi>v.</hi> 5, 6. in theſe words, <hi>We have found this Man a peſtilent Fellow, and a mover of Sedition among all the</hi> Jews <hi>throughout the world, and a Ring-leader of the Sect of</hi> Nazarens, <hi>who alſo hath gone about to profane the Temple;</hi> a great Charge without any colour of Truth, as <hi>Paul</hi> afterwards in his Defence declared, and ſaid alſo, <hi>Neither can they prove the things whereof they now accuſe me,</hi> v. 12, 13. <hi>But this,</hi> (ſaid he,) <hi>I confeſs, after the way they call Hereſie, ſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip I the God of my Fathers, believing all things which are written in the Law and the Prophets;</hi> and this indeed was his only Crime, for which they ſo perſecuted him. They yet further pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued him before <hi>Feſtus, Act.</hi> 25. <hi>The</hi> Jews <hi>there ſtood round about</hi> Paul, <hi>and laid many and grievous Complaints against him, which they could not prove,</hi> v. 7. <hi>And</hi> Paul <hi>anſwered,</hi> v. 8. <hi>neither</hi> (ſaid he,) <hi>againſt the Law of the</hi> Jews, <hi>neither againſt the Temple, nor yet againſt</hi> Caeſar, <hi>have I offended in any thing at all;</hi> yet his Innocency could not excuſe him from their violent Perſecuting of him, becauſe of the Heart-Enmity they had againſt him. Thus hath the Scripture noted, That the Enemies of good Men, and Goodneſs it ſelf, in the Ages of the World, did follow the Steps one of another, in manifeſting their Heart-Enmity againſt them and it, by charging them with many and notorious Crimes every where; to the end, that the Enemies own Proceedings might ſeem to be juſt, and only a Legal Perſecution of Malefactors, not a malicious purſuit of Innocents; and that they might bring Chriſt and good Men, into the ill Opinion both of the People, and of the Magiſtrates, the eaſier to prevail with them to aſſiſt in the Perſecution.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly. A third way that theſe envious Ones were found in, and which theſe divine Records have alſo obſerved, was, That they watched and ſought for Advantages to take hold of ſomething, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to accuſe Chriſt and the Saints; yea, they did frequently tempt them to ſpeak, by asking enſna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Queſtions, and ordering of others ſo to do, in order to the framing of an Accuſation againſt them; and did oft times wreſt their Words too: As the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> complaining, ſaying, 29.20. <hi>All who watch for iniquity are cut off, who make a Man an offender for a word, and layeth a ſnare for him who reproveth in the gate, and turn aſide the juſt for a thing of naught.</hi> Therefore the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Amos</hi> adviſeth, <hi>That the prudent ſhould keep ſilent in ſuch an evil time,</hi> Chap. 5.12, 13. And the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> reſolved ſo to do, in his time, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.1. (ſaith he there,) <hi>I will keep my mouth with a Bridle, while the wicked is before me;</hi> ſo well acquainted was he with the uſual way of the wicked in this matter. Thus did they do with <hi>Daniel,</hi> becauſe the King had advanced him above the Preſidents and Princes, <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.1, 2, 3, 4. <hi>They ſought occaſion againſt him, in the matters of the Kingdom, but they found none;</hi> fain would they have accuſed him, could they have found any Matter which they ſought for. The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> in his days, too, found theſe Attempts made upon him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.12. (ſaith he,) <hi>They alſo who ſeek my life, lay ſnares for me, and they imagin deceits all the day long;</hi> and in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.69. <hi>The proud hath forged a lye againſt me;</hi> again, in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 56. <hi>v.</hi> 5, 6. <hi>Every day they wreſt my words; all their thoughts againſt me for evil, they mark my ſteps, when they wait for my Soul;</hi> thus they commonly did every day, (ſaith he); After the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner did the unbelieving <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> deal with Chriſt and his Followers, in thoſe days, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.10. they there tempted Chriſt, <hi>There was a man who had his hand withered, and they asked Christ, ſaying, is it lawful to heal on the Sabbath day? that they might accuſe him;</hi> here they waited, and by a queſtion tempts Chriſt to ſpeak, that they might catch ſomething of Matter of Accuſation: Again, the Prieſts and Elders, as he was teaching, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.23. ſaid, <hi>By what au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41342:6"/> doſt thou theſe things? and who gave thee this authority?</hi> Here doubtleſs, they hoped for an anſwer, which they might have interpreted, to have carried in it ſome affront to Magiſtrates and Government, whereof they might have accuſed him, wherefore Chriſt refuſed to give them any direct anſwer: And more expreſly 'tis ſaid in the next Chap. <hi>v.</hi> 15. <hi>That the Scribes and Phariſees went and took counſel how they might entangle him in his talk;</hi> and in order hereto, they in the next verſe, ſent out ſome to him, ſaying, <hi>Maſter, we know that thou art true,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>neither careſt thou for any man: for thou regardeſt not the perſons of men; tell us therefore, what thinkeſt thou, is it lawful to give tribute to</hi> Caeſar <hi>or not?</hi> Here, no doubt, they expected ſome words from him, our of which they might have pick'd ſome Treaſon; which, by their way of Addreſſing themſelves to him, they thought they might have drawn him too; which wicked Deſign of theirs, Chriſt well perceived, as 'tis ſaid, <hi>v.</hi> 18. by him, <hi>VVhy tempt ye me,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Then Chriſt bid them give to</hi> Caeſar <hi>the things which are</hi> Caeſars, <hi>v.</hi> 21, 22. Again, <hi>Luke</hi> 6.7. <hi>The Scribes and Phariſees watched him whether he would heal on the Sabbath day, that they might find an accuſation againſt him;</hi> yea, they are ſaid, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.53. <hi>To have urged him vehemently, and to have provoked him to ſpeak many things, laying wait for him, and ſeeking to catch ſomething out of his mouth, that they might accuſe him;</hi> ſo unceſſant were they in their purſuit of Chriſt, whom they hated and would have deſtroyed. And further, the Evangeliſt <hi>Luke,</hi> Chap. 20. ſaith, <hi>They watched him, and ſent forth ſpies, who ſhould fain themſelves juſt men, that they might take hold of his words, that ſo they might deliver him into the power and authority of the Governor,</hi> v. 20. Here they thought ſurely, that Chriſt would be more free to talk with juſt Men, and ſpeak that to them, which he would for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to do before others, that ſo they might enſnare him, by inſinuating Diſſemblers, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon accuſe him; yet again, did they ſet upon him, <hi>John</hi> 8.3. <hi>They ſet before him a Woman taken in Adultery,</hi> and ſaid to him, <hi>v.</hi> 5. <hi>Moſes ſaid, that ſuch ſhould be ſtoned, but what ſayſt thou? This they ſaid,</hi> (as in the next verſe,) <hi>tempting him, that they might have to accuſe him;</hi> which Chriſt alſo perceived, as in the following verſes. So far alſo doth the Scripture take notice of this Way, which thoſe wicked and invidious Ones in thoſe days took, to expreſs their Heart-hatred againſt the Saints, and againſt Chriſt himſelf.</p>
            <p n="4">4thly. Another Way and Method wherein they proceeded againſt the Saints, Chriſt and his Followers, and againſt the Truth, to ſuppreſs them and it, and ſtop their growth, was this, They called Councils, conſulted together, deviſed, plotted and contrived Miſchief againſt them in ſecret, and how they might effect their Ends, as the Scripture hath Recorded; King <hi>Pharaoh, Exod.</hi> 1. when he had perceived the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to encreaſe, and he had a mind to prevent their growth, <hi>v.</hi> 9. he conſulted with his People, and ſaid, <hi>Come, let us deal wiſely with them, leſt they multiply,</hi> &amp;c. v. 10. then in the following verſes, they put Burthens on them heavier and heavier; but when that would not do, he deviſed to ſlay the Male Children, and charged the Midwives ſo to do; and charged alſo his People to caſt the Sons of the <hi>Hebrews</hi> into the River. So did their Enemies in <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> days, Chap. 4. when they had heard that the Walls were built, they contrived al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to prevent their further progreſs; Firſt, they mock them, ſaying, <hi>What do theſe feeble</hi> Jews <hi>do? will they fortifie themſelves,</hi> v. 1, 2. but when they ſaw that would not do, 'tis ſaid, <hi>v.</hi> 7, 8. <hi>That they were then very wroth, and conſpired all of them together, to come and fight againſt</hi> Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, <hi>and to hinder the work;</hi> altho what the <hi>Jews</hi> did, was by Authority from the King. In like manner did they in <hi>Ezra's</hi> days, Chap. 4. When the Adverſaries of <hi>Jadah,</hi> &amp;c. had heard that they builded the Temple, <hi>v.</hi> 1. they <hi>v.</hi> 2. came and pretended that they would build with them; this was their firſt Plot to weaken their hands in their Building; but when that would not do, they contrived, in the 4th and 5th verſes, and hired Counſellors againſt them, to fruſtrate their Progreſs all the days of <hi>Cyrus;</hi> and afterwards, <hi>v.</hi> 8. the Chancellor and Scribe, and the reſt, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted and wrote to the King a Charge againſt them of high Nature, as in the following verſes, which effected their Deſign, and ſtaid the Work, <hi>v.</hi> 21. ſo induſtrious were thoſe in their Conſults
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41342:6"/> and Contrivances, to hinder that Work which they hated. <hi>Haman</hi> plotted the ruin of all the <hi>Jews,</hi> becauſe <hi>Mordicay</hi> did not bow to to him; he deviſed a courſe in his Breaſt, and accordingly proceeded <hi>Eſther,</hi> Chap. 3. Of ſuch doings, the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> in his days complained to God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 35.7. <hi>Without cauſe</hi> (ſaith he there,) <hi>they have hid from me their net in a pit, which without cauſe they have digged for my Soul;</hi> and in the 15th verſe, <hi>The abjects gathered themſelves toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and I knew it not;</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 19, 20. <hi>They hate me without a cauſe: for they ſpeak not peace, but they deviſe deceitful matters againſt them who are quiet in the Land;</hi> the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> had taken ſpecial notice, that wicked Men in his days, did uſually contrive evil againſt ſuch who were inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and peaceable in the Land: And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38. he ſaid, <hi>That they alſo who ſought his life, did lay ſnares for him, and they did imagin deceits all the day,</hi> v. 12. Again, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.13. <hi>Fear</hi> (ſaid he,) <hi>was on every ſide, whilſt they took Counſel together againſt me, they deviſed to take away my life; and ſo</hi> (ſaid he,) <hi>they did againſt others too.</hi> Pſal. 94.21. <hi>They gathered themſelves toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt the ſoul of the righteous, and condemn the innocent Blood;</hi> thus did they in that day, conſult how they might take away the Life of them whom they hated, and how they might do it with the greateſt eaſe, ſecrecy, and ſecurity to themſelves they could. The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> yet further ſpreads this before God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 83. <hi>Be not ſtill, O God,</hi> (ſaith he,) <hi>v.</hi> 1. <hi>Why, what is the matter? Why,</hi> ſaith he, in the next verſes, <hi>Lo, thine Enemies make a tumult, and they have taken crafty counſel againſt thy people, and conſulted againſt thy hidden ones; they have ſaid, Come, lets cut them off from being a Nation, that the name of</hi> Iſrael <hi>be no more in remembrance, for they have conſulted together with one conſent; they are confederate againſt thee.</hi> 'Tis noted too, that the Preſidents and Princes in <hi>Daniels</hi> time, did take the ſame way with him, <hi>Dan.</hi> 6. When they ſaw the King had advanced him over them, verſes 1, 2, 3. they in the next verſes, becauſe they could not find occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion againſt him in the Matters of the Kingdom, which they had ſought to do; they conſulted and contrived to enſnare him in the Matter of his God, <hi>v.</hi> 5. and accordingly, they, in the next verſes, purſued the thing they had contrived, procured a Law in that Matter, and convicted him thereupon. After the ſame manner did the unbelieving <hi>Jews,</hi> and the <hi>Gentiles</hi> too, in thoſe days, contrive againſt Chriſt and his Followers, as it is written, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. when Chriſt had, <hi>v.</hi> 13. hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the withered Hand, <hi>The Phariſees,</hi> in the next verſe, <hi>went out, and held a Council againſt him, how they might deſtroy him;</hi> again, after Chriſt had ſpoken to them in a Parable, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. <hi>They</hi> in <hi>v.</hi> 15. <hi>went and took counſel, how they might entangle him;</hi> and afterwards, in the next verſes, they purſued their Contrivances; ſo <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. <hi>Then aſſembled together the chief Prieſts, and the Scribes, and the Elders of the people, unto the Palace of the High Prieſt; and conſulted that they might take Jeſus by ſubtilty, and kill him,</hi> in verſes 3 &amp; 4. The like Counſel they took again, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.1. <hi>to put him to death.</hi> Here the chief Men amongſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> were frequently in taking counſel how they might have deſtroyed this innocent and juſt One; ſuch was their Heart-hatred of him. Nay, when he had raiſed <hi>Lazarus,</hi> and the Fact was ſo evident that they could not deny it, <hi>John</hi> 11.44, 45. <hi>Then gathered the chief Prieſts and the Phariſees a Council; and ſaid, what do we! if we let him thus alone, all Men will believe on him,</hi> v. 47, 48. to prevent which, they were moſt induſtriouſly engaged. They did the like afterwards to the Apoſtles; when theſe had preached Chriſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 5. <hi>They were cut to the heart, and they took counſel to ſlay the Apoſtles,</hi> v. 33. Yea, when <hi>Paul</hi> had given over to perſecute the Saints, and had preached Chriſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 9. <hi>The fews,</hi> v. 23. <hi>took counſel to kill him too: And more than forty,</hi> Acts 23. <hi>had conſpired together, and bound themſelves under a Curſe not to eat or drink till they had killed him,</hi> v. 12, 13. <hi>and theſe had agreed with the chief Prieſts and Elders, how they ſhould have effected this Murther,</hi> v. 14, 15. Thus hath the Scripture declared and ſet forth, the ſeveral Conſults, Contrivances, Plots, and wicked Devices, that theſe wicked envidious Ones in thoſe Ages of the World, had made and deſigned againſt Chriſt, good and peaceable Men, according to that in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. <hi>They took counſel againſt the Lord and his Anointed,</hi> &amp;c. v. 2. &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:41342:7"/>5thly. A fifth Way that thoſe envious Ones, Unbelievers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> did take, in thoſe days, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs their Enmity againſt Gods People, Chriſt and his Followers, was this, They did procure, and Enact Laws and Decrees Civil and Eccleſiaſtical, on purpoſe both to enſnare, puniſh and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them: And to deter others from owning and following of them or their Doctrins; and under collour of ſuch Laws or Decrees, they did proceed to accuſe them as diſobedient, and ſo puniſh them thereupon; as the <hi>Pſalmiſt, Pſal.</hi> 94. intimated, that they did in his days; <hi>Shall the Throne of Iniquity</hi> (ſaith he,) <hi>v.</hi> 20. <hi>have fellowſhip with thee: who frame miſchief by a Law?</hi> And what they did upon theſe Laws, is expreſſed in the next verſe, in theſe words, <hi>They gather themſelves to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether againſt the ſoul of the righteous, and condemn innocent blood:</hi> The Holy Ghoſt takes notice on't here, that altho they ſeemed to do it by a Legal Proceſs, yet 'twas the Righteous, 'twas inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Blood, they condemned thereby, as <hi>Jezebel</hi> the Wife of <hi>Ahab,</hi> did with innocent <hi>Naboth,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21. when ſhe had ſeen <hi>Ahab</hi> diſcontent about the Vineyard, <hi>v.</hi> 5, 6. ſhe reſolved to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch <hi>Naboth</hi> out of the way, and that by colour of Law too; as 'tis ſaid there, <hi>v.</hi> 7. ſhe ſaid to <hi>Ahab, Doſt thou not govern the Kingdom of</hi> Iſrael? <hi>Let thine heart be merry: I will give thee the Vineyard of</hi> Naboth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In order to which, <hi>ſhe</hi> v. 8. <hi>wrote Letters in</hi> Ahabs <hi>name, and ſealed it with his Seal, and ſent the ſame to the Elders and the Nobles of the City, where</hi> Naboth <hi>dwelt;</hi> and by that Letter, in the next verſes, directs them to proceed againſt him in a Judicial way, but to ſet up falſe Witneſſes againſt him; to which the Nobles and Elders (reaſoning themſelves ſecure, having the Kings Commandment for it,) did comply, tho the way was deſperately wicked; they ſet up Witneſſes, Sons of <hi>Belial</hi> againſt him, judged, condemned and executed him, in the 11, 12, and following verſes. The Enemies of the <hi>Jews</hi> did, by falſe ſuggeſtions againſt them, procure a Decree from the King to ſtop their work of Building, in <hi>Ezra</hi> 4. <hi>Nebucadnezar</hi> the King, having ſet up an Image, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.1. and in the following verſes, Decreed, <hi>That all who heard the ſound of the Cornet,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſhould fall down and worſhip him, and that ſuch who did not, ſhould be caſt into the fiery Furnace;</hi> upon this, the <hi>Caldeans,</hi> v. 8. accuſed the <hi>Jews,</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 12. they ſaid, <hi>Theſe Men, O King, regard not thee, they ſerve not thy gods;</hi> upon which the King in great fury ſent for them, <hi>v.</hi> 13. and <hi>v.</hi> 19. in greater wrath commanded the Execution of them, according to that Law; which in the following verſes they performed: Here was a wicked Law or Decree, and upon this they condemned thoſe innocent and peaceable Men. And thus they dealt with <hi>Daniel</hi> himſelf too, in thoſe days; <hi>The Preſidents and Princes</hi> (who had hated him,) <hi>having ſought occaſion againſt him in the matters of the Kingdom, and found none;</hi> could not hit him upon any Law in that reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect; ſuch was his Faithfulneſs, and ſo good a Subject was he, <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.4, 5. They contrived a Law or Decree, on purpoſe, in the Matter of his God, that upon this they might ruin him; 'tis ſaid, <hi>v.</hi> 7. <hi>That all the Preſidents of the Kingdom, and the Governors, and the Princes, the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors and the Captains, had conſulted together to eſtabliſh a Royal Statute, to make a firm Decree, That whoſoever ſhall ask,</hi> &amp;c. and in the next verſes, they obtain a Confirmation thereof by the King, upon which they, <hi>v.</hi> 11. and ſo onward, proſecuted <hi>Daniel</hi> for praying to the true God, and caſt him into the Den of Lyons, (tho the Kings Heart was to deliver him); thus did they there frame this Law, and yet it confirmed upon this ſole Deſign, that they might take <hi>Daniel</hi> in the Matter of his God, and ſo diſpatch him. So did <hi>Haman</hi> alſo with the <hi>Jews</hi> in <hi>Mordicays</hi> days, when he had reſolved to have deſtroyed both <hi>Mordieai</hi> and the <hi>Jews,</hi> he applied himſelf to the King for a Decree to deſtroy them, which he obtained, and accordingly proceeded upon it till he was prevented, <hi>Eſther</hi> 4.6, 8, and following verſes. After the ſame manner the <hi>Jews</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves did in Chriſts time, under pretence of Law, they perſecuted Jeſus himſelf unto death, they brought him before <hi>Pilate</hi> the Judge, in open Court, and there charged him, and proſecuted him in a pretended regular way, <hi>Luke</hi> 23. Yea, and that they might terrifie others from confeſſing and owning of him in the World at that time, they made or agreed an Eccleſiaſtical Law too, That if any did confeſs him, they ſhould be Excommunicated; as 'tis expreſly ſaid, <hi>John</hi> 9.22.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41342:7"/> in theſe words, <hi>That the</hi> Jews <hi>had already agreed, that if any man did confeſs that he was Chriſt, that he ſhould be put out of the Synagogue;</hi> of which Law the <hi>Jews</hi> at that time ſtood in great fear, as is plain by the Parents of the blind Man, there ſpoken of in this Chap. they anſwered ſo ſhyly when the queſtion was asked them concerning their Son, for fear of this Law of Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, which they did afterwards actually put in Execution againſt their Son when he owned Chriſt, <hi>v.</hi> 34. And 'tis expreſly ſaid, <hi>John</hi> 7. <hi>That many ſaid, he is a good man,</hi> v. 12. <hi>Howbeit, no man ſpake openly of him for fear of the</hi> Jews, <hi>v.</hi> 13. And again, <hi>John</hi> 12. <hi>v.</hi> 42. 'tis ſaid, <hi>Among the chief Rulers alſo many believed on him, but becauſe of the Phariſees, they did not confeſs him, leſt they ſhould be put out of the Synagogue; for they loved the praiſe of men more than the praiſe of God;</hi> of which Law and the execution thereof, Chriſt had told his Diſciples, <hi>Before,</hi> Jo. 16. verſe, <hi>they will put you out of their Synagogues, they will execute thoſe Laws they have contrived on purpoſe to prevent mens confeſſing of me.</hi> Thus doth the Scripture Records evidence, that the wicked Ones in thoſe Ages, did take this Courſe alſo to prevent and deter Men from owning God, and Chriſt, and his Laws.</p>
            <p n="6">6thly. Yet a ſixth Way wherein they did evidence their Enmity againſt God and Chriſt, againſt the Saints and followers of Chriſt, was this, That when they otherwiſe could not, in a Legal Way, make out any of the Accuſations and Charges they had brought againſt them; and being reſolved to take them, they then did ſuborn, and ſet up falſe Witneſſes, Men of <hi>Belial,</hi> to ſwear againſt them, and affirm even whatever they had ſuggeſted to them; to whom the Magiſtrates in thoſe days, did eaſily give credit too, as the Scripture declared; That the Elders and Nobles, by <hi>Jezebels</hi> means, did in the caſe of <hi>Naboth,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21. when <hi>Jezebel</hi> there had written to them in the Kings Name, and under his Seal, (tho without his knowledge,) <hi>v.</hi> 8. and therein directed them, <hi>v.</hi> 9, &amp; 10. to ſet up <hi>Naboth</hi> on high among the People, and to ſet up falſe witneſſes; <hi>They,</hi> in <hi>v.</hi> 11, 12, 13. <hi>accordingly ſet up</hi> Naboth; and 'tis ſaid there, <hi>There came in two men, children of</hi> Belial, <hi>and witneſſed againſt him, ſaying,</hi> Naboth <hi>did blaſpheme God and the King;</hi> which they the Elders and Nobles, ſoon gave credit too, <hi>for they preſently carried him out and ſtoned him;</hi> here they ſhed innocent Blood, by falſe ſuborned Witneſſes, as they were commanded to do; tho they knew it to be a deſperate wicked thing ſo to do. The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> in his days, complained of ſuch dealings, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.69. and ſaid there, <hi>The proud hath forged a lie againſt me;</hi> and in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 35.11. he ſaid, <hi>Falſe witneſſes did ariſe up, they laid to my charge things which I knew not.</hi> After the ſame manner did the unbelieving <hi>Jews</hi> deal with Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, and with his Diſciples, in their days; as the Scripture alſo affirmeth, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. it is ſaid there, <hi>v.</hi> 59. <hi>That the chief Prieſts and Elders, and all the Council, ſought falſe witneſſes againſt Jeſus to put him to death;</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 60, and 61. <hi>At laſt came two falſe witneſſes, and ſaid, This Fellow ſaid,</hi> &amp;c. Thus the Holy Ghoſt takes notice, that the Chief Prieſts, Elders and Council, were principally engaged in this wickedneſs too; ſuch was their Heart Enmity againſt him, that they could not bear with his being on the Earth; therefore they regarded not what wicked Courſe they took to ſend him hence. So did the Libertines and others, in the caſe of <hi>Stephen, Act.</hi> 6. <hi>When they were not able to reſiſt his wiſdom,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>v.</hi> 10. <hi>They then,</hi> in the next verſes, <hi>ſuborned men, who ſaid, We have heard him ſpeak Blaſphemies,</hi> &amp;c. and afterwards, <hi>v.</hi> 12, &amp; 13. <hi>they ſet up thoſe falſe witneſſes before the Council againſt him.</hi> This Charge they had framed againſt him, and endeavored to prove, (tho by falſe Witneſſes, by Perjury,) that they might ſeem to be juſt, and to perſecute him in a Legal manner, according to <hi>Moſes</hi> Law, and ſo put him to death; for in the next verſes, <hi>They ſtir up the Elders and Scribes, and People,</hi> (who were forward enough of themſelves againſt him,) <hi>and took him, brought him before the Council;</hi> where they produced their ſuborned Men, who ſaid of him, <hi>That this man ceaſed not to ſpeak blaſphemous words againſt the holy Place and the Law,</hi> &amp;c. So far hath theſe divine Records taken notice of this Way and Procedure of theſe wicked perſecuting and invidious Men, in thoſe Ages of the World.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:41342:8"/>7thly. And that the wicked Enemies of God, of Jeſus Chriſt, and of his People and Laws, in thoſe days, might carry their Matters the more plauſible, and obtain an Opinion in Magiſtrates of their own Loyalty; and that they might get the greater countenance to their Proceedings, and awe and engage other inferior Magiſtrates and Officers, (contrary to their own Inclinations and Judgments,) to aſſiſt them in their revengeful Acts, they were found in this ſeventh Method or crafty Courſe. They did moſtly pretend themſelves to be ſpecial Friends to the Kings and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors, and Laws Eccleſiaſtical and Civil, in thoſe days, in all they did this way; and that Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors, Government and Laws, were much concerned in all that they alledged againſt thoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whom they had accuſed; and that therefore only, were they ſo zealous againſt them in thoſe Matters; altho in truth, 'twas only proceeding from their own envious and revengeful Hearts within them; Examples and Inſtances of which the Scripture hath alſo Recorded. In <hi>Ezra's</hi> days, when the Adverſaries of the <hi>Jews</hi> being vexed at them, <hi>Ezra</hi> 4.1, 2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the Chancellor and others wrote to the King againſt them, <hi>v.</hi> 6. and amongſt other things, they in their Letter ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaints him, that they were building that rebellious and bad City, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and in <hi>v.</hi> 13. they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terreſt the King in theſe words, which they ſuggeſted, <hi>Be it known unto the King, That if this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty be built,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>then will they not pay Tole, Tribute and Cuſtom, and ſo thou ſhalt endamage the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue of the Kings;</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 13. <hi>Now,</hi> ſaid they, <hi>becauſe we have maintainance,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>it is not meet for us to ſee the Kings diſhonour, therefore have we ſent, and certified the King;</hi> here they pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the Kings diſhonour and the loſs he was like to bear, was that they were concern'd about, and that therefore the King was concerned to prevent it; when all this proceeded only from their Heart-Enmity againſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> as ſuch, as 'tis ſaid in <hi>v.</hi> 1. &amp; <hi>v.</hi> 5. of the ſame 4th of <hi>Ezra.</hi> In like manner did <hi>Sanballat</hi> and other their Enemies, in <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> days; when they had underſtood, <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. that <hi>Nehemiah</hi> had come with Authority to build the City, they were ſorely grieved, <hi>v.</hi> 10. <hi>It grieved them exceedingly that there was come a Man to ſeek the welfare of the Children of</hi> Iſrael; their Heart-Enmity againſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> made the Favor that the King ſhew'd to them, to be Grief to thoſe; and contrary to true Loyalty, they endeavor to oppoſe what theſe were do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by Commiſſion from the King; as in <hi>v.</hi> 19. They ſaid to them, <hi>will ye rebel againſt the King?</hi> thus they ſuggeſted, that they would rebel againſt the King, altho they knew the King did allow what the <hi>Jews</hi> did in that matter; ſo again, the ſame <hi>Sanballat,</hi> in a Letter ſent by his Servants to <hi>Nehemiah, Chap.</hi> 6. told <hi>Nehemiah</hi> thus, <hi>v.</hi> 5, 6, 7. <hi>It is reported,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that thou and the</hi> Jews <hi>think to rebel, for which cauſe thou buildeſt the Wall, that thou mayſt be their King,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and ſhall it be reported to the King according to theſe words;</hi> thus theſe Mens hatred of the <hi>Jews,</hi> made them ſuggeſt theſe things againſt them, wherein the King muſt be concerned; altho, what the <hi>Jews</hi> did then, was by the Kings own Commiſſion, which Loyal Subjects ſhould have encouraged. <hi>Haman</hi> afterwards took the ſame way againſt <hi>Mordicai</hi> and the <hi>Jews, Eſther</hi> 3. he being full of wrath againſt <hi>Mordicai,</hi> becauſe he did not bow before him, <hi>v.</hi> 5. he (the better to compaſs his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengeful Deſign, and being a great Favourite of the King,) preſently interreſts the King in the matter, and like a very Loyal Subject, tells the King, <hi>v.</hi> 8. thus, <hi>There are a certain people,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and their Laws are divers from all people;</hi> and what then? <hi>O neither keep they the Kings Laws;</hi> and in the next words, <hi>Therefore 'tis not for the Kings profit to ſuffer them; let it be written that they be deſtroyed,</hi> v. 9. here he ſeemed to be greatly concerned for the King in this matter, as a very Loyal Man; but the Holy Ghoſt hath there ſet forth, that he did this only to effect what his malicious Heart had reſolved ſo to do, in revenge againſt <hi>Mordicai,</hi> even to deſtroy him and all the <hi>Jews,</hi> who were a peaceable and profitable People. So when the Enemies of <hi>Shadrach, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhach</hi> and <hi>Abednego,</hi> would have deſtroyed them, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. they preſently there, <hi>v.</hi> 12. concerns the King therewith, in theſe words, <hi>There are certain</hi> Jews, <hi>&amp;c. Theſe men, O King, have not regarded thee, they ſerve not thy God,</hi> &amp;c. which enraged the King preſently; by which they had their End in the next verſes: Here theſe Men pretended to the King, that theſe <hi>Jews,</hi> in affront to the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41342:8"/> King, would not worſhip the Image; when their Enemies knew the contrary, that they were good Subjects, only in that matter could not actually obey. And ſo dealt the Preſidents and Princes with <hi>Daniel</hi> himſelf, whom they hated, becauſe the King had advanced him above them, <hi>Dan.</hi> 6. their deſign was to deſtroy him; and the better to effect it, they preſently concern the King and the Law in the matter, for both which, they ſeemed to be zealous; and having, on purpoſe to take him, procured a Law or Decree to have been made; they <hi>v.</hi> 13. ſaid thus to the King, <hi>Daniel who is of the captivity,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>regardeth not thee, O King, nor the Decree which thou haſt ſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> &amp;c. Here they did inſinuate that the King was concerned in Honor, to vindicate his Authority and Law againſt <hi>Daniel,</hi> as a deſpiſer of both; altho they very well knew 'twas duty to God, not diſloyalty to the King that made him to pray to God, contrary to that Decree; of which alſo the King himſelf was ſo ſenſible, that 'tis ſaid of him, <hi>v.</hi> 14. <hi>He was ſore diſpleaſed with himſelf, and ſet his heart on</hi> Daniel <hi>to deliver him, and he labored till the going down of the Sun to deliver him;</hi> to which theſe pretenders to Loyalty, (having their hearts ſet to deſtroy <hi>Daniel,</hi>) would not yield, their love to the King would not bring them to ſtoop to his deſire, becauſe it contradicted their deſign; but now they preſs the King with the Law, and ſhew their zeal for the puniſhment of Offenders againſt the Law, <hi>v.</hi> 15. as if the King had not power to diſcharge the Offenders; that their Heart-Enmity againſt <hi>Daniel,</hi> and their purpoſe to deſtroy him, not the Kings Honor nor true zeal for Juſtice, made theſe Men thus warm againſt <hi>Daniel,</hi> is here very evident. Thus did the unbelieving <hi>Jews,</hi> and other Enemies of Jeſus Chriſt and of his Followers, in after Ages, againſt Chriſt himſelf and his Apoſtles, in thoſe days, <hi>Luke</hi> 23. They there out of a deſign to deſtroy Chriſt, accuſed him as an Enemy to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> interreſts <hi>Caeſar</hi> in the matter, that they might ſeem to perſecute Chriſt, rather from Loyalty than ſecret Hatred and Enmity they carryed againſt him; as in <hi>v.</hi> 2. they ſaid, <hi>We found this Fellow,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>forbidding to give Tribute to</hi> Caeſar, <hi>ſaying, That he himſelf is a King;</hi> by this they deſigned, as an expedient, the eaſier to get <hi>Pilate</hi> to paſs Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt him, as is evident, <hi>John</hi> 19 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r when they there perceived that <hi>Pilate</hi> was willing to releaſe Chriſt, and probably would have done it; in <hi>v.</hi> 12. <hi>The</hi> Jews <hi>cryed out, If thou let this Man go, thou art not</hi> Caeſars <hi>friend: for whoſoever maketh himſelf a King, ſpeaketh againſt</hi> Caeſar; upon which words, 'tis ſaid in the next verſe, <hi>That</hi> Pilate <hi>brought him out;</hi> here was great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernedneſs for <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſeemingly, yet Envy was the motive, and Chriſts Life the deſign only, which <hi>Pilate</hi> very well knew, for he found no fault in him; and its expreſly ſaid ſo, <hi>That he knew that the Prieſts had delivered him up for envy,</hi> Mark 15.10. Tho this very thing did ſo awe <hi>Pilate,</hi> (as they deſigned it ſhould,) againſt his inclination and judgment, that he delivered this Juſt One into their hands to be Crucified. After the ſame manner did they with the Apoſtles and Diſciples of Chriſt afterwards, in <hi>Act.</hi> 7. 'tis ſaid there, <hi>v.</hi> 5. <hi>That the</hi> Jews <hi>who believed not, moved with envy, took ſome baſe Fellows with them, and laid hold on</hi> Jaſon <hi>and ſome others,</hi> v. 6. <hi>and brought them before the Rulers, and there immediately they interreſt</hi> Caeſar <hi>and his Laws in the buſineſs,</hi> v. 7. and ſay, <hi>Theſe do all contrary to the Decrees of</hi> Caeſar, <hi>ſaying, that there is another King Jeſus:</hi> So again, <hi>Act.</hi> 18. <hi>The</hi> Jews <hi>there made an inſurrection againſt</hi> Paul, <hi>and brought him before the Judgment Seat,</hi> v. 12, &amp; 13. they charge him with breach of their Eccleſiaſtical Laws, ſaying there, <hi>This Fellow perſuadeth men to worſhip God contrary to the Law,</hi> or eſtabliſhed mode; by which, no doubt, they engaged many readily to aſſiſt them in their perſecuting of him; tho <hi>Galio</hi> drave them from the Judgment Seat, and would not meddle in thoſe Laws, <hi>verſes</hi> 15, 16. Thus doth the Scripture note, that the Enemies of the Saints and of the Truth it ſelf, in thoſe Ages, did walk in this Path alſo, in order to the effecting of their envious and revengeful Purpoſes.</p>
            <p n="8">8thly. But when this Method neither did do the Work ſo effectually as they deſigned, then they proceeded againſt them in an eighth Way, that was, They did in moſt places ſtir up baſe Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, and all ſorts of People; and together with them, did they tumultuouſly take hold of them
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41342:9"/> hale them to Priſon and before Magiſtrates, and oftentimes contrary to all Laws and Juſtice, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Peace, beat them, baniſh them, and haſtily ſtone them, and go about to kill them; as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſaid of them, in his days, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 53.4. in theſe words, <hi>Who eateth up my people as they eat Bread;</hi> of which doings Jeſus foretold and acquainted his Diſciples, that they were to bear a ſhare in, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. <hi>They will</hi> (ſaith he there,) <hi>deliver you up to the Council, and they will ſcourge you in their Synagogues; and ye ſhall be brought before Governors and Kings for my ſake,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>v.</hi> 17, 18. Nay, Chriſt himſelf eſcaped not ſuch rude and illegal Dealings, as 'tis taken notice of, <hi>Luke</hi> 4.28, 29. in theſe words, <hi>They were filled with wrath, and roſe up and thruſt him out of the City, and laid him to the brow of the hill, whereon the City was built, that they might caſt him down headlong;</hi> and <hi>Luke</hi> 22. <hi>The multitude, with the chief Prieſts and Captains of the Temple and El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, came to take him,</hi> v. 47. <hi>with ſwords and ſtaves, as againſt a Thief,</hi> as Chriſt ſaid, <hi>v.</hi> 52. and theſe, in this tumultuous manner, <hi>led him to the High Prieſts houſe,</hi> v. 54. &amp; v. 63, &amp; 64. <hi>They mock him and ſmote him, having blindfolded him, they ſtroke him on the face, ſaying, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie who it is who ſmote thee;</hi> and in <hi>v.</hi> 1. of the next Chap. it is again ſaid, <hi>That the whole mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude aroſe and led him to</hi> Pilate: Here the common Rabble, as well as the great Ones, hurry'd him about, mock and beat him in a tumultuous and an illegal manner. So did the Enemies of the <hi>Jews</hi> before, in <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> days, conſpire to do; <hi>Nehem.</hi> 4. when they had obſerved, that all their other Attempts for hindring their Building would not do, (the <hi>Jews</hi> having the Kings Authority with them,) <hi>Sanballat and others here being very wroth,</hi> v. 7. <hi>did conſpire all of them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to come to fight againſt</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>to hinder it;</hi> ſuch was their Enmity againſt the <hi>Jews</hi> here, for building by the Kings Authority, that how Loyal ſoever they otherways pretended to be, yet here did they agree moſt rebelliouſly and wickedly, to hinder the Building by fighting againſt them. They readily obeyed the King in <hi>Ezra's</hi> time, when his command was to cauſe the Work to ceaſe; but now when they were by the Kings command to build, they would diſobey, and in an hoſtile and rebellious manner hinder it. The like did the perſecuting <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves, in the Apoſtles days too, in <hi>Act.</hi> 4. <hi>As the Apoſtles ſpake unto the people, the Prieſts, and the Captain of the Temple, and the Sadduces came upon them,</hi> v. 1. <hi>and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they taught,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>they laid hands on them, and put them into hold,</hi> v. 2, and 3. ſo again, <hi>Act.</hi> 5. when they had underſtood that the Apoſtles had done Miracles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> v. 15, 16. <hi>The High Prieſt roſe up and all thoſe who were with him, (which is the Sect of the</hi> Sadduces,) <hi>and were filled with indignation,</hi> v. 17. and in the following verſes, <hi>They laid their hands on the Apoſtles, and put them into common Priſon. Stephen</hi> was ſo illegally and riotouſly handled, <hi>Act.</hi> 6. when the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines and others had diſputed with him, <hi>and not able to reſiſt the ſpirit and wiſdom by which he ſpake,</hi> v. 9, 10. <hi>They,</hi> in v. 12. (to confute him.) <hi>ſtirred up the People, and the Elders, and the Scribes, and came upon him, caught and brought him to the Councel;</hi> and again, in the next Chap. 'tis ſaid, <hi>v.</hi> 54. that when they had heard what <hi>Stephen</hi> ſaid, <hi>they were cut to the heart, and they gnaſhed on him with their teeth;</hi> and in <hi>v.</hi> 57. and ſo onward, <hi>That they ran upon him with one accord, and caſt him out of the City and ſtoned him.</hi> It is recorded alſo of <hi>Saul, Acts</hi> 8. <hi>v.</hi> 3. <hi>That he made havock of the Church, entring into every houſe, and haleing men and women, committing them to Priſon;</hi> which he, after his Converſion, did confeſs, <hi>Act.</hi> 22. in theſe words, <hi>v.</hi> 5, 6. <hi>I perſecuted this way to the death, binding and delivering into Priſon, both men and women, I went unto</hi> Damaſcus <hi>to bring them which were there bound unto</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>to be puniſhed;</hi> and in <hi>v.</hi> 19. ſaid he to the Lord, <hi>I impriſoned and beat in every Synagogue, them who believed on thee.</hi> Thus did others deal with <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, when he became a preacher of Chriſt, and with <hi>Sylas, Act.</hi> 16. <hi>Paul</hi> having caſt out the Spirit of Divination out of the Damſel, <hi>v.</hi> 18. <hi>her maſters,</hi> v. 19, 20. <hi>caught</hi> Paul <hi>and</hi> Sylas, <hi>drew them into the Market-place to the Rulers, and brought them to the Magiſtrates,</hi> and there accuſed them for Troublers of the City; upon which, <hi>The multitude roſe up together againſt them, and the Magiſtrates commanded to beat them, and when they had laid
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41342:9"/> many ſtripes upon them, they caſt them into Priſon,</hi> v. 22, 23. All which Proceedings were illegal, violent and tumultuous, and ought not to have been done to them; as <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf told them, <hi>v.</hi> 35, &amp; 36. (when the Magiſtrates had ſent to diſcharge them,) in theſe words, <hi>They have beaten us openly uncondemned, being</hi> Romans, <hi>and have caſt us into Priſon, and now do they thruſt us out privily? nay verily, let them come themſelves and fetch us out;</hi> and in the next verſe, <hi>The Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates feared when they heard that they were</hi> Romans, <hi>and they came and be ſought them to go out.</hi> Even ſo did the unbelieving <hi>Jews, Act.</hi> 13. upon their obſervation that multitudes did hear the Word, <hi>were filled with envy, and ſpake againſt thoſe things which were ſpoken by</hi> Paul, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> v. 45. and upon their ſecond ſpeaking, <hi>v.</hi> 46. and ſo on, <hi>The</hi> Jews <hi>v.</hi> 50. <hi>ſtirred up the devout and honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Women, and the chief Men of the City, and raiſed Perſecution againſt</hi> Paul <hi>and</hi> Barnabas, <hi>and expelled them out of their coaſts;</hi> here, when contradicting and blaſphemy would not do, they ſtir up a Tumult, and by illegal and violent means drive them away: And this courſe they did un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſantly follow, <hi>Act.</hi> 14. <hi>v.</hi> 2. it is Recorded in theſe words, <hi>That the unbelieving</hi> Jews <hi>ſtirred up the Gentiles, and made their minds evil affected againſt the Brethren;</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 5. as the effect on't, 'tis ſaid, <hi>That when there was an aſſault made, both of the Gentiles and of the Jews, with their Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, to uſe them deſpitefully and to ſtone them, they fled;</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 19. <hi>They purſued them, came where they were, and having perſuaded the People, and ſtoned</hi> Paul, <hi>drew him out of the City,</hi> &amp;c. Thus did they here, moſt unjuſtly, riotouſly and illegally, perſecute <hi>Paul</hi> and others, ſtirred up the People every where ſo to do: Again, they did walk in the ſame Steps in <hi>Act.</hi> 17. 'tis ſaid of them thus, in <hi>v.</hi> 5. <hi>They being moved with envy, took to themſelves certain lewd Fellows of the baſer ſort, and gathered a Company, and ſet the whole City in an uprore, and aſſaulted the houſe of</hi> Jaſon; and <hi>v.</hi> 6. <hi>They drew him to the Magiſtrate;</hi> here theſe made great Riots, dealt rudely, ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally and violently with Chriſt and the Saints, when by Law they could not effect their Purpoſes: And again, <hi>v.</hi> 13. of the ſame Chap. <hi>They purſued</hi> Paul <hi>to</hi> Barea, <hi>and ſtirred up the people there too.</hi> And in <hi>Act.</hi> 18. <hi>The</hi> Jews <hi>there made an inſurrection with one accord againſt</hi> Paul, <hi>and drew him to the Judgment Seat,</hi> v. 12. and when <hi>Galio</hi> refuſed to meddle with the matter, <hi>becauſe there was no matter of wrong that he was charged with, or wickedneſs,</hi> verſes 14, 15, 16. <hi>They then took</hi> Soſthenes, <hi>the chief Ruler of the Synagogue, and beat him before the Judgment Seat;</hi> ſuch Outrages as theſe did they then commit. The like riotous, illegal and tumultuous Ways, did the Silver-Smiths take againſt <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 19. when they ſaw that their Craft was like to be ſet at naught, if People believed <hi>Diana</hi> to be no Goddeſs, <hi>v.</hi> 24. and ſo on, <hi>they were full of wrath,</hi> v. 28. <hi>and the whole City was filled with confuſion, and having caught</hi> Gaius <hi>and others,</hi> v. 29. <hi>they ruſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with one accord into the Theater;</hi> they were in a great Tumult and Riot in the City, in the next verſes, which whole Proceeding was illegal, as the Town Clerk afterward told them, in theſe words, <hi>v,</hi> 36, 37. and ſo on, <hi>Ye ought to be quiet and to do nothing eaſily, for ye have brought hither theſe Men who are neither robbers of Churches, nor yet blaſphemers of your Goddeſs; wherefore, if the craftsmen have any matter againſt any man, the Law is open,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>let them implead one another; if it be concerning other matters, it ſhall be determined in a lawful Aſſembly, for we are in danger of being called in queſtion for this days uprore,</hi> &amp;c. This courſe was not allowable here, among the Heathens themſelves. The <hi>Jews</hi> again dealt ſo with <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 21.27, 28. <hi>They ſtirred up all the people, and laid hands on him, and cryed out, Men of</hi> Iſrael <hi>help, this is the man,</hi> &amp;c. upon which cry, <hi>all the City was moved,</hi> in the next verſes, <hi>and the people ran together, and they took</hi> Paul <hi>and drew him out of the Temple, and went about to kill him, till the Captain came, whom when they ſaw, they left of beating of him; yea, more than fourty conſpired together, and reſolved to kill him,</hi> Act. 23.12. Thus hath the Holy Ghoſt taken notice of this Practice of the wicked Enemies of God and his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in thoſe days, and that it was very common, in thoſe days: The Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> intimated in the 2d. Chap. of his Epiſtle, <hi>v.</hi> 6, <hi>&amp;</hi> 7. ſaith he there, <hi>Do not rich men oppreſs you, and draw you before the Judgment Seats? do not they blaſpheme that worthy Name by which ye are called?</hi> Theſe Interrogations, implies an Affirmation, that they did ſo, uſed ſo to do.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:41342:10"/>
            <p>Neither here did their Envy and Enmity againſt the Saints in Old Teſtament times, nor againſt Chriſt and his Followers, in the New, end and proceed no further; no, they were never ſatisfied while any of thoſe remained alive upon the Earth; like thoſe <hi>Act.</hi> 22.22. who cryed out againſt <hi>Paul,</hi> in theſe words, <hi>Away with ſuch a Fellow from the Earth, for it is not fit he ſhould live;</hi> right or wrong, let him be taken off the Earth: They therefore perſecuted them to the death; that did they deſign, that did they purſue by all the before-mentioned ways: Nay, ſuch was their bitter Enmity, that if the Magiſtrate at any time, ſeemed to be willing to acquit any of them becauſe of their Innocency, they cryed out upon him, away with him, and told <hi>Herod</hi> he was no Friend to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> if he let him go; and that rather then Jeſus ſhould be acquitted, they deſired a moſt notorious Criminal ſhould be ſaved, even <hi>Barabbas,</hi> who for Sedition and Murther in the City, was caſt into Priſon; they preferred the moſt vile Men to that moſt innocent and unblamable One. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inſtances of this too, the ſame divine Records hath delivered down; as the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> ſaid in the general, <hi>Cap.</hi> 5.6. of rich Men, <hi>Ye have condemned and killed the juſt, and he doth not reſiſt you.</hi> So ſaid the <hi>Pſalmiſt, Pſal.</hi> 37. <hi>The wicked hath drawn out the ſword,</hi> v. 14. <hi>to ſlay ſuch as be of an upright Converſation:</hi> And again, in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44.22. <hi>For thy ſake are we killed all the day long, we are counted as Sheep for the ſlaughter:</hi> And more particularly, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. <hi>Cain</hi> there having brought an Offering, and <hi>Abel</hi> another to the Lord, and the Lord reſpecting <hi>Abels</hi> and not <hi>Cains,</hi> v. 3, 4, 5. <hi>Cain,</hi> v. 8. upon this very account, <hi>roſe up againſt him, and ſlew him.</hi> In like manner did <hi>Joſephs</hi> Brethren intend to do with him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 37. they perceiving that their Father loved him more than he did them, envyed him, or hated him, <hi>v.</hi> 3, &amp; 4. and in <hi>v.</hi> 18. <hi>Seeing him afar of, they conſpired againſt him to ſlay him;</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 20. ſaid, <hi>Come now, let us ſlay him, and caſt him into ſome pit,</hi> &amp;c. Nothing leſs than his Life would ſatisfie ſome of them at leaſt; ſuch was their Envy againſt their innocent Brother, in that day. <hi>Jezebel, Ahabs</hi> Wife, after <hi>Elijah</hi> had cauſed the Prophets of <hi>Baal</hi> to be ſlain, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18. ſhe <hi>Chap.</hi> 19. underſtanding the matter by the King, ſent a Meſſenger to <hi>Elijah,</hi> in <hi>v.</hi> 2. ſaying, <hi>So let the gods do, and more alſo; if I make not thy life as the life of one of them, by to morrow about this time;</hi> ſuch was her hatred of him, that nothing but his Life was deſired by her; but he fled. So <hi>Hamans</hi> fiery Enmity againſt <hi>Mordicai,</hi> could be no way quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but by his Life, and the Life of all the <hi>Jews, Heſter</hi> 9.5, 6. when <hi>Mordicai</hi> would not bow, and give <hi>Haman</hi> reverence to him, he was full of wrath, and thought ſcorn to lay hands on <hi>Mordicai</hi> alone, but he and all the <hi>Jews</hi> muſt be deſtroyed together; which he purſued in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing verſes. After the ſame manner did they purſue Chriſt himſelf to the death, <hi>John</hi> 18. and becauſe the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves could not proceed ſo far as to put him to death by their Law, (as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves confeſſed <hi>v.</hi> 31.) they therefore brought him before <hi>Pilate</hi> to be judged, that they might by pretence of that Authority put him to death, which afterwards they did, (tho ſo juſt a One as he was, and by <hi>Pilate</hi> declared ſo to be,) as is in the next Chap. recorded; yea, when <hi>Pilate</hi> would have releaſed him, becauſe of his Innocency, <hi>Luke</hi> 23.14, 15. the <hi>Jews</hi> cryed out, <hi>v.</hi> 21. <hi>Crucifie him, Crucifie him;</hi> right or wrong they muſt have his life; this was in their hearts to have, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears further, <hi>v.</hi> 22, 23. <hi>The Scribes and Phariſees having beforehand,</hi> Mat. 12.14. <hi>taken coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel how they might deſtroy him.</hi> Chriſt did forewarn his Diſciples and Followers, and intimated unto them, that they ſhould be ſo dealt with too, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. <hi>The Brother</hi> (ſaith he there, in <hi>v.</hi> 21.) <hi>ſhall deliver up the Brother to death, and the Father the Child, and the Children ſhall riſe up againſt their Parents, and put them to death;</hi> according to which they frequently did in thoſe days, as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doth evidence. When Chriſt had raiſed up <hi>Lazarus, John</hi> 11.43, 44. <hi>The chief Prieſts,</hi> in Chap. 12. <hi>v.</hi> 10, 11. <hi>conſulted, that they might put</hi> Lazarus <hi>alſo to death, becauſe that by reaſon of him many of the Jews believed on Jeſus;</hi> So <hi>Acts</hi> 5. becauſe the Apoſtles had preached Chriſt before the Council there, they preſently conſulted <hi>to ſlay them,</hi> v. 33. The ſame Spirit was <hi>Saul</hi> of, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.1. he there conſented to the death of <hi>Stephen;</hi> and <hi>Act.</hi> 9.1. its ſaid of him, <hi>That he yet breathed out threatnings and ſlaughter againſt the Diſciples of the Lord;</hi> which he himſelf acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41342:10"/> he had done, <hi>Act.</hi> 22. <hi>v.</hi> 4. in theſe words, <hi>I perſecuted this way to the death;</hi> ſo dealt he and others with <hi>Stephen,</hi> upon his preaching of Chriſt, <hi>Act.</hi> 7. <hi>They ran upon him with one accord, and caſt him out of the City, and ſtoned him,</hi> v. 57, 58. <hi>Herod the King,</hi> Act. 12. <hi>ſtretched forth his hand to vex certain of the Church,</hi> v. 1. and <hi>v.</hi> 2. <hi>he killeth</hi> James <hi>with the ſword; yea, there were more than fourty of the Jews, who bound themſelves in a curſe not to eat or drink till they had killed</hi> Paul, <hi>v.</hi> 12, 13. <hi>of which they acquainted the chief Prieſts and Elders, and directed them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a way to effect it too,</hi> in the next verſes: And again, <hi>Act.</hi> 25. <hi>The chief Prieſts and chief of the</hi> Jews <hi>deſigned to kill him,</hi> and in order to it, <hi>they deſired the favor of</hi> Feſtus <hi>to ſend for</hi> Paul <hi>to</hi> Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, <hi>v.</hi> 2. and <hi>v.</hi> 3. 'tis ſaid, <hi>That there were lyers in wait in the way to kill him;</hi> thus did they purſue their very Lives by all their former Methods. For which doings, the Apoſtle complained, in his Firſt Epiſt. to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> Chap. 2. <hi>v.</hi> 14, 15. thus, <hi>The</hi> Jews <hi>who both killed the Lord Jeſus, and their own Prophet, and have perſecuted us,</hi> &amp;c. Thus hath the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture alſo taken notice, that their Enmity was ſuch, that by way of revenge, nothing leſs would ſerve them than the very Lives of the Saints and Servants of God, yea, of Chriſt himſelf; in thoſe days, they could not reſt till they had taken them off the Earth.</p>
            <p>Then Thirdly, As the Holy Ghoſt hath by Scripture Records, ſhewn the bitter Enmity that was ſeated in the Hearts of the wicked, in thoſe days, againſt the Saints and Holineſs it ſelf; and the ſeveral Methods thoſe Men then took, to expreſs or evidence their Enmity againſt them and it, for their ſuppreſſion and to hinder the growth of Holineſs; ſo alſo hath the ſame Spirit deluded down to after Age, many of the Grounds and Cauſes of ſuch their Enmity againſt, and hatred of them, and which put them upon Perſecuting the one and Oppoſing the other.</p>
            <p>The Firſt and Original Cauſe why they did perſecute at that rate in thoſe days, was from that irreconcilable Enmity which they brought into the World with them againſt God, againſt Chriſt who came forth from him, againſt his Laws and Government, as is ſaid, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.7. <hi>The carnal mind is enmity againſt God, cannot be ſubject to him;</hi> they cannot endure any thing of the Spirit whilſt they are in the Fleſh, in the ſame State in which they came into the World; they cannot bear with the Light which ſhineth in the Law of God, becauſe their Works are Works of Darkneſs; and hence came their Hearts to be at enmity and hatred againſt the Saints and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God, ſuch who owned God and his Laws, and ſubjected themſelves to him and it, or did preach up Subjection to the ſame; and ſo conſequently, to perſecute their Perſons, and oppoſe and obſtruct the ſpreading of the Truth, by all the ways they could; as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> impli'd they did, when he ſpake in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. thus, <hi>Why do the heathen rage, and the people imagin vain things? The Kings of the Earth ſet themſelves, and the Rulers take councel together againſt the Lord and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Anointed; ſaying, Let us break their Bands, and caſt their Cords from us,</hi> &amp;c. they could not bear them, they would not be bound by them, <hi>v.</hi> 1, 2. Here their Enmity againſt God, and Chriſt and his Laws, put them upon imagining, taking councel how to eaſe themſelves of the good Men of God and Chriſt; and as a conſequent, how to eaſe themſelves of all thoſe who did ſubmit to thoſe Laws of God and walk with him; as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> again did cleerly aſſert, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 83. in theſe words, <hi>v.</hi> 2. <hi>Thine enemies make a Tumult, and they who hate thee lift up the head,</hi> v. 2. what follows, <hi>why,</hi> v. 3. <hi>they have taken crafty counſel againſt thy people, and conſulted againſt thy hidden ones;</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 4. they ſaid, <hi>Come and lets cut them off from being a Nation;</hi> here firſt they hate God himſelf, and then conſult to deſtroy his People. To this cauſe doth the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> reduce it in thoſe days, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44.22. <hi>For thy ſake</hi> (ſaith he there,) <hi>are we killed all the day long, we are accounted as ſheep for the ſlaughter;</hi> it was for Gods ſake they hated him, and muſt needs kill his whom they could reach. <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſpake after the like manner, Chap. 15. <hi>v.</hi> 15. he prays thus, <hi>Revenge me of my Perſecutors,</hi> &amp;c. and uſeth this as the Argument, <hi>Know,</hi> (ſaith he,) <hi>that for thy ſake have I ſuffered rebuke;</hi> it was for his faithfulneſs to God. So Chriſt told his Diſciples, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. <hi>That they ſhould be brought before Governors and Kings but for his name ſake,</hi> v. 8 they
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41342:11"/> hated Chriſt, ſo puniſhed his Followers; and again, <hi>v.</hi> 22. <hi>Ye ſhall be hated of all men for my name ſake;</hi> their hatred of Chriſt is aſſigned here, as the cauſe of their hatred againſt his Followers; as Chriſt further hinted to the <hi>Jews</hi> in the Parable he ſpake to them, <hi>Luke</hi> 19. concerning a Noble Man, <hi>v.</hi> 12. where in <hi>v.</hi> 14. 'tis ſaid, <hi>That the Citizens hated him, and ſent forth a Meſſenger af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him, ſaying, We will not have this Man to reign over us.</hi> The unbelieving <hi>Jews</hi> would have none of his Government, 'twas too ſtrict for them; they hate him, and from thence 'twas that they could not endure ſuch who either preached him up as Lord, or his Laws as that by which they ought to be ruled, or did ſubmit themſelves to him or it; and they perſecuted them as intollerable, uſed all means to hindier the publication of his Laws, or him as Lord and Saviour, and to hinder others ſubmiſſion to him and it; for which Chriſt pronounced againſt them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.13. in theſe words, <hi>Wo to you Scribes and Phariſees, Hypocrites, for ye ſhut up the Kingdom of Heaven againſt Men; for ye neither go in your ſelves, neither ſuffer ye them who are entring to go in:</hi> They from their hatred to Chriſt would not be ſubject to him and his Laws themſelves, nor would they ſuffer others to be ſubject, but did oppoſe and perſecute them, and contradict and blaſpheme the Doctrin, perſuading People to ſubjection to him; and becauſe the Light which ſhone in his Life and Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin, and in his Followers, did diſcover and reprove their wicked Natures and Deeds of Darkneſs, it could not be born with; as Chriſt told his unbelieving Brethren, <hi>John</hi> 7. <hi>The world cannot hate you, but me it hateth,</hi> v. 7. Why? <hi>Becauſe</hi> (ſaid he,) <hi>I teſtifie of it, that their works are evil:</hi> Again, <hi>John</hi> 3.19, 20. <hi>Light is come into the world, but men love darkneſs rather than light.</hi> Why? <hi>Becauſe their deeds are evil, for every one who doth evil, hateth the light, leſt his deeds ſhould be reproved,</hi> or diſcovered. Thus hath the Scripture aſſigned this to be the Original, or one main Cauſe of the wicked Ones Enmity againſt, and perſecuting of the Saints, and their high oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt the Light of the Goſpel and true Holineſs it ſelf.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly. It did ariſe from this, That the Saints, the called of God, did evidence themſelves to have been changed from what they were by Nature, and by Practice too; they owned and loved what formerly they had hated; they had declared themſelves not to be of the World, could not run with the ſame exceſs of Riot with others, as they had done, do as formerly they did; but their Lives and Works did contradict and reprove the Lives of their Perſecutors. Now this they could not bear, therefore did they hate them, and brake out againſt them in thoſe various Methods and Ways before noted; as the Scripture ſaith, <hi>He who doth evil, hateth the light,</hi> John 3.20. No ſooner did <hi>Saul</hi> (whom they had ſo much loved formerly,) leave his perſecuting of the Saints, and being changed, did evidence the ſame by joyning with them, and in preaching up what his Heart had been againſt; but the <hi>Jews</hi> hated him, and ſtudied to kill him, <hi>Act.</hi> 9.19, 20, and ſo on; and that it would be ſo, Chriſt had told his before, <hi>John</hi> 15. <hi>If</hi> (ſaith he there, <hi>v.</hi> 19.) <hi>ye were of the world, the world would love his own; but becauſe ye are not of the world, but I have choſen you out of the world, therefore doth the world hate you:</hi> Here did he intimate to them, that no ſooner ſhould they evidence by their good Life, that they are called out of the World, and off from the evil Courſes thereof, but the World hated them upon that very account, and thereupon perſecuted them; as 'tis written <hi>Habak.</hi> 1.13. in thoſe days, <hi>That the wicked devoured the man who was more righteous than he:</hi> And 'tis expreſly ſaid, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.5. <hi>That</hi> Cain <hi>was angry with his Brother</hi> Abel, <hi>becauſe the Sacrifice</hi> Abel <hi>offered, was accepted and not his, and he,</hi> in <hi>v.</hi> 8. <hi>ſlew him;</hi> altho the reaſon given of his Non-acceptance was, becauſe he did not well, <hi>v.</hi> 7. and his Brother did; as the Holy Ghoſt doth affirm in theſe words, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.12. <hi>Not as</hi> Cain <hi>was of that wicked one, and ſlew his Brother; and wherefore ſlew he him? becauſe his own Works were evil and his Brothers righteous;</hi> upon which account the Saints are exhorted, in the next verſe, not to marvail, tho the World do hate them. When <hi>Elijah</hi> had but evidenced his Change, by reproving King <hi>Ahaziah</hi> for his ſending to the God of <hi>Eckron,</hi> to enquire if he ſhould recover, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 2, 3, 4. the King was ſo enraged againſt him, <hi>that he</hi> v. 9. <hi>ſent a Captain, with his fifty to fetch him, and the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:41342:11"/> Captain and his men were deſtroyed by fire from Heaven; yet he ſent another,</hi> and tho he was deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>ſent a third,</hi> in the next verſes; ſuch was his bitterneſs againſt <hi>Elijah</hi> for this cauſe only. So ſaid the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> alſo, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.19 and ſo on, <hi>They who hate me are multiplyed,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>They alſo who render evil for good are mine Adverſaries, becauſe I follow the thing which good is;</hi> there is the cauſe why wicked Men are adverſaries to good Men, only becauſe they are good now, and not ſuch as formerly they were. So again, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.12. <hi>The wicked</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt,) plotteth againſt the juſt;</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 14. <hi>They have drawn out the ſword to ſlay ſuch as be of an upright Converſation.</hi> So ſaid <hi>Amos</hi> too, <hi>Chap.</hi> 5.10. <hi>They hate him who reproveth in the gate, they abhor him who ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth uprightly,</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 12. <hi>They afflict the juſt;</hi> Here the Scripture aſſigned no other cauſe, why theſe Men did envy, hate and perſecute them, but this, that thoſe hated and perſecuted Ones were juſt, righteous and good, and reproved their Perſecutors for the contrary; this was ſufficient to render them obnoxious to the wickedſt hatred and ſcorn. <hi>Herod</hi> in thoſe days, committed <hi>John</hi> to Priſon, and would have put him to death, becauſe <hi>John</hi> had told him, <hi>it was not lawful to marry his Brother</hi> Philips <hi>Wife,</hi> Mat. 14.3, 4, 5. The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> declares this too in his time, 1. <hi>Epist. Chap.</hi> 4. ſpeaking of the unconverted Gentiles thoughts of the converted Ones, becauſe they could not do as they had done, and as the wicked ſtill did, <hi>v.</hi> 3, 4. in theſe words, <hi>Wherefore they think it ſtrange, that ye run not with them into the ſame acceſs of Ryot, ſpeaking evil of you;</hi> Here they ſpeak evilly of the Saints, becauſe they could not be ſo wicked as they; they wondred at their change, could no longer think or ſpeak well of them: So that the Scripture doth make it evident, that the wicked unbelieving Ones did in thoſe days, hate and perſecute the Saints as Saints, and only becauſe they were new Creatures, called out of the World, Men of a good Life, could not be and do as others did, or do as they themſelves ſometimes had done; by which they did reprove the Spirits and Doing of thoſe wicked Perſecutors.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly. A third cauſe or ground which the Holy Ghoſt in Scripture hath aſſigned, from whence the Envy and perſecuting Spirits of wicked Men did ariſe; that was the Pride, height of Spirit, and revengeful Nature which was in them: Such was their Pride, that they would not ſeek God themſelves, nor bear with thoſe who did, as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſaid, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.4. <hi>That the wicked through the pride of his countenance, will not ſeek God;</hi> and in <hi>v.</hi> 8. 'tis ſaid of him, <hi>That in the ſecret places doth he murther the innocent, his eyes are privily ſet againſt the poor;</hi> as their Pride here would not permit them to ſeek God, ſo it ſet them againſt the Saints, innocent Ones who did ſeek God. The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> again, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.69. ſaid, <hi>The proud have forged a lie againſt me:</hi> And again, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 123.4. he ſaith, <hi>Our Soul is exceedingly filled with the ſcorning of them who are at eaſe, and with the contempt of the proud:</hi> Here the Holy Ghoſt takes notice, that the Pride of their Hearts did render the Saints the objects of their Scorn, and put them upon forging of lies againſt them. This very thing ſet <hi>Haman</hi> into ſo great hatred againſt <hi>Mordicai,</hi> and made him ſo reſolute on re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge againſt him and all the <hi>Jews, Hester</hi> 3. his proud Heart could not bear with <hi>Mordicai,</hi> becauſe he did not ariſe and do him Reverence, as is expreſſed <hi>v.</hi> 5. in theſe words, <hi>When</hi> Haman <hi>ſaw that</hi> Mordicai <hi>bowed not, nor did him reverence, then was</hi> Haman <hi>full of wrath;</hi> and in the next verſe, <hi>He thought ſcorn to lay hands on</hi> Mordicai <hi>alone, but ſought to deſtroy all the</hi> Jews <hi>with him;</hi> ſuch were his revengeful Purpoſes from the dreadful Pride of his Heart. Hence it came to paſs that the Preſidents and Princes in <hi>Daniels</hi> time, ſo much hated him, ſtudied to revenge, and took thoſe courſes to execute it upon him; <hi>Dan.</hi> 6. He being now advanced by King <hi>Darius</hi> over all the Preſidents and Princes, <hi>v.</hi> 1, 2. their proud hearts could not bear it; and this put them upon ſeeking occaſion againſt him concerning the Kingdom, <hi>v.</hi> 4. and finding none; ſo good a Subject and innocent. Man was he; they in the next verſes reſolves to take him in the matters of his God, procured a Law, and purſued him in the ways they had deviſed, till they had gotten him into the Lions Den, tho the King himſelf would have ſaved him. From the like pride of Heart the Libertines and others, who were diſputing with <hi>Stephen, Act.</hi> 6. <hi>and not able</hi> v. 9. <hi>to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41342:12"/> reſiſt the ſpirit and wiſdom by which he ſpake,</hi> nor able to bear to be ſilenced by <hi>Stephen;</hi> they in the next verſes evidenced their Pride and revengeful Spirits, they confute him <hi>by ſuborning Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, ſtirring up the People, Elders and Scribes againſt him, caught him and carryed him before the Council.</hi> The like Spirit did the <hi>Jews</hi> evidence in thoſe days, in their Behaviour towards the Man who was born blind, <hi>John</hi> 9. when he had by ſuch convincing Arguments which they could not reſiſt, proved Chriſt to be of God, <hi>v.</hi> 30. and ſo on: The Pride of the Phariſees being ſuch, that they could not bear to be put to ſilence by ſuch a poor unlearned Man as he was; therefore they <hi>v.</hi> 34. took this courſe; they firſt ſay to him, <hi>Thou waſt altogether born in ſin, and doſt thou teach us?</hi> And they Excommunicated him: Having no better Argument, they confuted him this way, and revenged upon him after this ſort. Thus hath the Scripture noted, that the wicked Ones envy againſt good Men often did ariſe from the Pride of their Hearts and revenge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Nature.</p>
            <p n="4">4thly. A fourth cauſe or ground from whence they ſo maligned and perſecuted the Saints, Chriſt himſelf and his Followers, in thoſe days did ariſe from their great ignorance of God himſelf, of Chriſt, and of the Saints, in perſecuting of whom they perſecuted Chriſt, as he told <hi>Saul, Act.</hi> 9.4. As 'tis ſaid of <hi>Pharaoh, Exod.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Who is the Lord that I ſhould let</hi> Iſrael <hi>go? I know not the Lord</hi> (ſaid he,) <hi>therefore I will not let</hi> Iſrael <hi>go;</hi> his ignorance of God here, made him oppreſs and grieve Gods People ſtill, and purſue them afterwards. So it was with <hi>Saul, Act.</hi> 9. when Chriſt had ſaid, <hi>Why perſecuteſt thou me?</hi> Saul <hi>anſwered, Who art thou, Lord?</hi> v. 4, 5. Here his ignorance of Jeſus was the cauſe why he perſecuted him and his Saints. Chriſt intimates this alſo to be the cauſe why the <hi>Jews</hi> hated him and perſecuted him to the death; <hi>Luke</hi> 23. when they were Crucified of him, he there prays for them in theſe words, <hi>v.</hi> 34 <hi>Father forgive them, for they know not what they do. Had they known him</hi> (ſaith the Scripture,) <hi>they would not have crucified the Lord of glory,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.8. Their ignorance here was the cauſe of their perſecuting Acts, and of their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant Mind againſt him and his. The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> took it for granted, that in thoſe days it did proceed from hence, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.4. thus he ſaid, <hi>Have all the workers of iniquity no knowledge, who eat up my people as they eat bread?</hi> Which Saying ſtrongly implies, that had they had know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge they would not, they could not have done ſo. The Apoſtles alſo in their time, did intimate the like, and aſſigned the Ignorance of the <hi>Jews</hi> to be the cauſe of their malignity againſt Chriſt and his, <hi>Act.</hi> 3. they tell them <hi>v.</hi> 15. <hi>That they had killed the Prince of life;</hi> but <hi>v.</hi> 17. ſaith to them thus, <hi>Now Brethren, I wot that through ignorance ye did it, as did alſo your Rulers:</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, <hi>Act.</hi> 13. ſaid the Apoſtle to them in <hi>v.</hi> 27. <hi>That they who dwell at</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>and their Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, becauſe they knew him not, nor yet the voices of the Prophets, (which are read every Sabbath-day,) they have fulfilled them in condemning him;</hi> and in <hi>v.</hi> 28. <hi>Tho they found not cauſe of death in him, yet deſired they</hi> Pilate <hi>that he ſhould be ſlain.</hi> Upon the ſame Foundation of Ignorance, <hi>Paul</hi> acknowledgeth that he went, <hi>Act.</hi> 26. <hi>I verily thought with my ſelf,</hi> v. 9. <hi>that I ought to do many things contrary to the name of Jeſus.</hi> The <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves <hi>John</hi> 9. did own their ignorance of Chriſt, <hi>v.</hi> 29. (ſaid they,) <hi>As for this Fellow we know not from whence he is;</hi> all the undeniable Evidences they had had, that he was of God, did not enlighten them nor convince them, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they perſiſted to envy and perſecute him; and as to ſuch who profeſſed to own him, <hi>many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied him,</hi> Titus 1.16. <hi>being unto every good work reprobate,</hi> (or void of Judgment). In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the Scripture declared, that afterwards they perſecuted and hated good Men upon this account, or from hence, that they knew not God, Chriſt, or them, 1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Therefore the world knoweth us not, becauſe it knew not him;</hi> and as Chriſt had told his Diſciples, <hi>John</hi> 15.20. <hi>If they perſecut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me, they will alſo perſecute you;</hi> and in the next verſes gives the reaſon of it in theſe words, <hi>All theſe things will they do unto you for my name ſake, becauſe they know not him who ſent me:</hi> So a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, <hi>John</hi> 16. <hi>The time cometh</hi> (ſaid Chriſt there,) <hi>v.</hi> 2. <hi>that whoſoever killeth you, ſhall think he doth God good ſervice;</hi> the reaſon of which he gives in the next verſe, in theſe words, <hi>Theſe things
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41342:12"/> will they do, becauſe they have not known the Father, nor me.</hi> From this Root alſo, doubtleſs it came to paſs, that the Chriſtians in that Age were called a Sect, <hi>Act.</hi> 28. and were ſo much ſpoken againſt every where; as <hi>Pauls</hi> Countrymen ſaid, <hi>v.</hi> 2. <hi>We deſire</hi> (ſaid they to him,) <hi>to hear of thee what thou thinkeſt, for as concerning this Sect, we know that every where 'tis ſpoken againſt;</hi> right or wrong they ſpeak againſt them and their way, becauſe they underſtood them not nor it. <hi>Peter</hi> in general aſſigns this as the cauſe of Mens ſpeaking evil of many things, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Thoſe</hi> (ſaith he, ſpeaking there of wicked Men,) <hi>as natural brute Beaſts,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſpake evil of the things which they underſtood not;</hi> nay, 'tis marvellous, that the malice of the <hi>Jews</hi> againſt Chriſt did ſo blind them, that when <hi>Judas</hi> came to them, and acknowledged to them that he had betrayed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Blood, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.3, 4. <hi>They ſay, What is that to us? look thou to that;</hi> when they had been the chief Inſtruments in the betraying of him, and putting him to death. Thus doth the Scripture Records note this Cauſe among others, of which Mens envy againſt Chriſt himſelf, and his Followers in thoſe days, againſt the Saints of old before his time, and why they perſecuted them.</p>
            <p n="5">5thly. A fifth cauſe or ground yet, which the ſame Scripture doth aſſign or declare of theſe their Spirits and Doings, was from a cauſeleſs and carnal Fear which they had conceived; that if the Saints of old, Jeſus Chriſt and his Followers, in thoſe days, were ſuffered amongſt them, or if their Doctrin ſhould have prevailed, then theſe would grow to big for them, and would with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw their ſubjection from their Rulers, Rebel, uſurp Authority, and would be had in greateſt Eſteem and Repute by the People, and ſo derogate from the Honor, Eſteem, Authority and Rule of thoſe who did thus envy and perſecute them; they were ready to think that all Men would believe on Chriſt, and that all the World would go after him, if they ſhould have let Him and his Follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers alone, and ſhould not have ſtopped their courſe, as they did declare, <hi>John</hi> 11.48. <hi>If we let him thus alone</hi> (ſaid they there,) <hi>all men will believe on him, and the</hi> Romans <hi>ſhall come and take away both our Place and Nation:</hi> And again, <hi>John</hi> 12.19. (they ſaid,) <hi>Perceive ye how ye pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail nothing? behold, the world is gone after him;</hi> thus did their cauſeleſs Jealouſie work to Envy and Hatred, and Perſecution. This made the Chief Prieſts and Scribes ſo highly diſpleaſed, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21. when they had ſeen Chriſt to have ſuch Eſteem among the People, and the ſame ſo evidenced <hi>by the multitudes ſpreading of their Garments, decking the Ways where he did ride, with Branches, and crying out Hoſanna to the Son of</hi> David, <hi>bleſſed is he who cometh in the name of the Lord, Hoſanna in the Higheſt,</hi> v. 8, 9, 15. and upon this, they <hi>v.</hi> 23. demanded of Chriſt, <hi>by what authority he did thoſe things?</hi> as if he were about to uſurp Authority, or at leaſt that he did it againſt or without Authority. Particular inſtances of this cauſe or ground too, not a few the Scripture takes notice of, as in <hi>Exod.</hi> 1. The King there was (without cauſe,) jealous that the <hi>Jews</hi> there would grow too great and numerous, and Rebel, therefore conſulted to prevent their increaſe by dealing hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with them; his Jealouſie is expreſſed <hi>v.</hi> 9, 10. in theſe words, <hi>The Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>are more and mightier than we. Come, let us deal wiſely with them leſt they multiply, and it come to paſs that when there falleth out any War, they join alſo to our Enemies and fight againſt us.</hi> This cauſeleſs Fear put him upon dealing cruelly with them, in order to prevent their growth, as in the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing verſes; upon which account alſo <hi>Joſephs</hi> Brethren went, <hi>Gen</hi> 37. they ſuſpecting by his Dreams, and his Fathers ſhew of love to him, that <hi>Joſeph</hi> would be greater than they, <hi>v.</hi> 4. and the 8, &amp; 11. they thereupon are ſaid there, <hi>to hate him, and envy him;</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 19, 20. of the ſame Chap. <hi>they conſulted to ſlay him:</hi> They could not bear with the thoughts of this, that he ſhould be greater than they in his Fathers Heart, nor ſuperior unto them in after-times, which they had gueſſed his Dreams did intimate that he ſhould be; therefore they hate him, and reſolve to prevent the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof to paſs, by taking away of his Life; tho God purpoſed to advance <hi>Joſeph</hi> to ſave them alive, as <hi>Joſeph</hi> afterwards told them, <hi>Gen.</hi> 45.5. This Spirit is taken notice of alſo in <hi>Joſhua</hi> from the ſame ground, in <hi>Moſes</hi> time, <hi>Numb.</hi> 11.26. <hi>When</hi> Eldad <hi>and</hi> Medad <hi>had propheſied in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:41342:13"/> the Camp, the young man preſently</hi> (thinking <hi>Moſes</hi> was clouded ſomewhat by this,) <hi>told</hi> Moſes <hi>on't,</hi> v. 27. and <hi>v.</hi> 28. ſaid, <hi>My Lord,</hi> Moſes <hi>forbid them;</hi> which Spirit of Envy in <hi>Joſhua,</hi> and the cauſe on't too <hi>Moſes</hi> perceived, and blamed him for it, in theſe words, in the next verſes, <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vieſt thou for my ſake? would God that all the Lords people were Prophets, and that the Lord would put his Spirit upon them all;</hi> doubtleſs, <hi>Joſhua</hi> here thought that none ſhould have the honor of a Spirit of Propheſie but <hi>Moſes;</hi> or if they had, they ſhould not ſhew it, as being eclipſing to <hi>Moſes</hi> Glory; and this ſtirred up this Envy in him. For this cauſe alſo did <hi>Saul</hi> eye and envy <hi>David</hi> in that day, and ſought his Life; <hi>David</hi> had gotten far into the opinion of his Fellow Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, through his prudent Behavior in the Kings buſineſs; and <hi>Saul</hi> feared that he would uſurp the Kingdom too doubtleſs, which he intimated in theſe words. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18. <hi>When the Women came after the overthrow of the</hi> Philiſtines, <hi>ſinging,</hi> in <hi>v.</hi> 6, 7. <hi>that</hi> Saul <hi>had ſlain his thouſands, and</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid <hi>his ten thouſands, he</hi> v. 8. <hi>was very wroth, and the ſaying diſpleaſed him; and he ſaid, they have aſcribed to</hi> David <hi>his ten thouſand, and to me thouſand, and can he have more but the Kingdom?</hi> The Effect followeth in the next verſes; <hi>Saul</hi> from that day following eyed <hi>David,</hi> and reſolved and endeavored to kill him; and <hi>Chap.</hi> 19.1. <hi>He gave order to his Son and Servants to kill him.</hi> Yea, he was alſo wroth with his Son <hi>Jonathan</hi> upon the ſame grounds, for <hi>Jonathans</hi> ſake, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19. when <hi>Jonathan</hi> had been excuſing <hi>Davids</hi> abſence, <hi>v.</hi> 28, 29. <hi>Sauls anger was kindled againſt</hi> Jonathan, v. 30. and he ſaid unto him, <hi>Do not I know that thou haſt choſen the Son of</hi> Jeſſe <hi>to thine own confuſion,</hi> &amp;c. and in the next verſe, he ſaid, <hi>As long as the Son of</hi> Jeſſe <hi>liveth upon the ground, thou ſhalt not be eſtabliſhed, nor thy Kingdom; wherefore ſend and fetch him to me, for he ſhall ſurely die:</hi> Here <hi>Sauls</hi> apprehenſion that <hi>David</hi> did eclipſe his Glory, and that the People had too much eſteem for <hi>David,</hi> and that he might prove diſloyal and uſurp the Kingdom, and that it could not be ſure to him or his Son if <hi>David</hi> lived, was the great cauſe of his envy and malice againſt <hi>David,</hi> and his purſuing of his Life; altho <hi>David</hi> had fully evidenced his Duty and Loyalty to <hi>Saul</hi> all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long; and eminently in that, when <hi>Saul</hi> had been twice in the power of his hands, that he might have ſlain him, he would not hurt him, not revenge himſelf, yea, and reſcued him from thoſe with him who would have done it; all which <hi>Saul</hi> himſelf acknowledged, as it is at large 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.4, 5, 6, 17. <hi>Chap.</hi> 26.8, 9.10, 11, 25. After the ſame manner did <hi>Herod</hi> the King againſt Chriſt in thoſe days, and from the ſame cauſe or ground, <hi>Mat.</hi> 2. He having heard that Chriſt was born, and that ſome had come to him to worſhip him, <hi>v.</hi> 1, 2, 3. <hi>He was troubled and all</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem <hi>with him:</hi> He now began to be jealous, that this Chriſt the King of the <hi>Jews,</hi> might poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly take away his Power or leſſen him, and he thereupon reſolves to prevent it; and <hi>v.</hi> 8. ſends to enquire after him, under pretence that he would worſhip him, but (as is evident by the Sequel,) it was that he might kill him; for <hi>v.</hi> 16. it is ſaid, <hi>That when he ſaw that he was mocked of the wiſe men, he was very wrath, and ſent forth, and ſlew all the Children which were in</hi> Bethlehem, <hi>and the coaſts thereof, from two years old and upwards, according to the time which he had diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enquired of the wiſe men:</hi> Here rather than he would endanger his Honor and Authority, (which he had cauſeleſly feared if Chriſt lived,) he (that he might be ſure to his Chriſt,) ſhed the innocent Blood of many Children. Upon the ſame grounds went the Chief Prieſts and Phariſees, in <hi>John</hi> 11.47, 48. in their envy againſt, and perſecuting of Chriſt; ſaid they in their Council, <hi>What do we do? for this man doth many miracles. If we let him alone all men will believe on him; and the</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans <hi>ſhall come and take away both our Place and Nation:</hi> Here were they jealous, that if Chriſt did go on, he would get ſuch Eſteem and Honor, that it would endanger their Honor and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity too, that they ſhould be leſſened among the People; and this ſet them at enmity againſt Chriſt, and upon perſecuting of him, and uſing of all means to render Him and his Doctrin contemptible, and not to be endured. Upon this account too, the Adverſaries of the <hi>Jews</hi> dealt ſo with them, <hi>Ezra</hi> 4. They (hearing that the <hi>Jews</hi> were building the Temple, <hi>v.</hi> 1.) preſently in the 12, &amp; 13. and following verſes, conceived a cauſeleſs Fear that theſe would Rebel, withhold the Kings due,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41342:13"/> and diſhonor the King; and ſo did they tell the King in theſe words, <hi>The</hi> Jews <hi>are come unto</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem <hi>building the rebellious and bad City,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Be it known unto the King, That if this City be builded,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>they will not pay Tole,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and its not meet for us to ſee the King diſhonored;</hi> which Letter of theirs begot the like jealouſie in the King, and thereupon he commanded their Work to ceaſe, <hi>v.</hi> 20, 21. So alſo 'tis recorded of the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves, that they ſuſpected Chriſt (becauſe he was called <hi>King of the</hi> Jews,) that he would grow too great, and vail their Glory; and therefore did they perſecute and hate him; therefore did they tell <hi>Pilate</hi> thus, <hi>John</hi> 19.12. <hi>If thou let this man go thou art not</hi> Caeſars <hi>Friend; for whoſoever maketh himſelf a King, ſpeaketh againſt</hi> Caeſar, and <hi>v.</hi> 15. when <hi>Pilate</hi> ſaid to them, <hi>Shall I Crucifie your King?</hi> they anſwered, <hi>We have no King but</hi> Caeſar: So did their fear of their own falling into Infamy and Diſgrace amongſt the People, cauſe them alſo to hinder the preaching of Chriſt to be the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> and to have been riſen from the Dead, by all the means they could, and to perſecute the Preachers of the Goſpel; for they knew well, that if the People ſhould once believe that indeed he was the Chriſt, the Son of God, all thoſe who had had a hand in perſecuting and ſlaying him, would have been judged murtherers of him, (as the Apoſtle <hi>Act.</hi> 5. did affirm they were, <hi>v.</hi> 30.) and ſo all their Honor and Credit among the People; that this was upon their Heart, the Holy Ghoſt in the ſame Chap. notes, <hi>v.</hi> 24. 'tis ſaid, <hi>When the Chief Prieſts and the Captain of the Temple had heard</hi> what the Apoſtles had preached, and done in this Name of <hi>Jeſus, they doubted of them whereto this would grow;</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 27, 28. <hi>They took them and brought them before the Council; and the High Prieſt asked them, ſaying, Did not we ſtraitly command you, that you ſhould not teach in this name? and behold, you have filled</hi> Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem <hi>with your Doctrin, and intend to bring this mans Blood upon us;</hi> of which, tho they had been guilty of, yet would they not that notice ſhould be taken of that wickedneſs, leſt they ſhould fall into diſeſteem amongſt the People. Upon this ground alſo was it, that <hi>Haman</hi> hated <hi>Mordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cai</hi> at that rate, and ſought his Life; he thought that <hi>Mordicai</hi> clouded his Honor, and further feared that <hi>Mordicai</hi> might get ſome favor at Court, becauſe he remained ſtill in the Kings Gate and would not bow to him; therefore did <hi>Hamans</hi> jealous Heart work how to deſtroy him, as is expreſſed, <hi>Heſter</hi> 3. it is ſaid there, <hi>v.</hi> 5. <hi>That when</hi> Haman <hi>ſaw that</hi> Mordicai <hi>bowed not, nor did him reverence, then was</hi> Haman <hi>full of wrath;</hi> and thereupon in the following verſes, he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts both his and his, and all the <hi>Jews</hi> deſtruction: Here the fear of the deminution of his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, or obſtructing of the heigth he aſpired too, put him upon hating of <hi>Mordicai,</hi> and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voring his ruin; as is yet more plain from his own words, <hi>Chap.</hi> 5. after he had given an account to his Friends there, throughout the beginning of the Chapter, of all his Honor and Favor at Court, and other his Advantages; he <hi>v.</hi> 13. ſpake thus, <hi>All this availeth me nothing, ſo long as I ſee</hi> Mordicai <hi>the</hi> Jew <hi>ſitting at the Kings Gate;</hi> ſtrongly did his Jealouſie work within him, leſt <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicai</hi> ſhould be in Favor and check his; that all he had availed him nothing, therefore makes a Gallows to hang <hi>Mordicai</hi> on, in the next verſe. Thus was this noted to have been one cauſe, why Men (wicked Ones,) have hated and perſecuted others, in thoſe Ages of the World.</p>
            <p n="6">6thly. A ſixth ground of their wrath and violence againſt good Men and Things in thoſe days, and of which the Scriptures giveth an account, was the blind Zeal of ſome, for the Heatheniſh and Idolatrous Worſhip; others for that Religion they were born and bred up in, the Traditions, Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies and Cuſtoms of the <hi>Jews,</hi> of which they were ſo tender and ſo jealous of looſing or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering, that they could not bear with the appearance of any thing which looked that way, but preſently did fly out into rage and violence againſt all Men and Doctrins that ſeemed to thwart it, or like to diſgrace or diſparage it; as it was ſaid of <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36. <hi>v.</hi> 14. <hi>That the chief of the Prieſts and the Prophets tranſgreſſed very much, after all the abominations of the Heathen, and polluted the houſe of the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. and they had habituated themſelves ſo to do, that this was the effect, <hi>v.</hi> 15. <hi>That when God had ſent to them by his Meſſengers, becauſe he had compaſſion on his people, and on his dwelling place; They</hi> v. 16. <hi>mocked the meſſengers of God, deſpiſed his word,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41342:14"/> and miſuſed his Prophets:</hi> Their cuſtom to worſhip in that falſe way, made them now not able to bear with a reprroof or perſuaſion, to return to worſhip again after the way which God himſelf had preſcribed; ſo zealous were they for that which they had been uſed to in thoſe days; therefore did they perſecute and miſuſe the Meſſengers, whom God had ſent to have turned them from their Heatheniſh way of worſhiping; which alſo the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> noted in his time, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. He propheſied that which ſhould come to paſs in Chriſts time, <hi>Why</hi> (ſaith he there,) <hi>do the heathen rage, and the people imagin a vain thing? The Kings of the earth ſet themſelves, and the Rulers take counſel to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether againſt the Lord and againſt his Anointed, ſaying, Lets break their bands aſſunder, and caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way their cords from us:</hi> When the Lords Anointed ſhould come, he would by his Laws alter the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> ways of worſhiping, according to their old Law, Traditions and Cuſtoms, and intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a new, as the Law of God before did contradict and forbid the Heathen Worſhip, which neither the one nor the other could bear with (while unconverted); therefore would they rage, imagin and take counſel againſt God and Chriſt, how to break their Bands, and to caſt away their Cords; they would none of Chriſts Government or Laws; of which alſo Chriſt himſelf in his days ſpake to his Diſciples, <hi>John</hi> 16. <hi>v.</hi> 2. that this blind Zeal ſhould put them upon killing of the Oppoſers thereof; <hi>The time cometh</hi> (ſaith he there,) <hi>that whoſoever killeth you, will think he doth God good ſervice:</hi> Their opinion of their own falſe Way, ſhould be ſo ſtrong, that it ſhould prompt them to deſtroy any who ſhould preach or practice the contrary, as for inſtance it came to paſs. Such was <hi>Pauls</hi> Zeal before his Converſion, <hi>Act.</hi> 8. 'tis ſaid of him, <hi>v.</hi> 3. <hi>That he made havock of the Church, entring into every houſe, and haleing men and women, and committing them to priſon,</hi> the cauſe of which, was his zeal for his Religion, as himſelf acknowledged, <hi>Act.</hi> 22.3, 4. in theſe words, <hi>I was zealous towards God as ye all at this day; and I perſecuted this way unto the death,</hi> &amp;c. All this, as the conſequent of his miſtaken Zeal, as he ſaid, <hi>Acts</hi> 26. <hi>v.</hi> 9. <hi>I verily thought with my ſelf, that I ought to do many things contrary to the name of</hi> Jeſus, <hi>which things I alſo did;</hi> and the particulars he named in the next verſes; <hi>Being exceeding mad againſt them, I perſecuted them,</hi> &amp;c. And again, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.13. he declared it in theſe words, <hi>Ye have heard of my Converſation in times paſt in the</hi> Jews <hi>Religion, that beyond meaſure I perſecuted the Church of God and waſted it;</hi> The grounds and reaſons ſtirring him up hereto, was his miſtaken Zeal, as he himſelf ſaith in the next verſe, in theſe words, <hi>And profited in the</hi> Jews <hi>Religion above many of mine equals in mine own Nation, being more exceeding zealous of the Traditions of my Fathers:</hi> Here, his blind Zeal, he ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily thought he ought to do as he did, (he having been bred up in the ſtrict obſervation of the Law, and of the Jewiſh Traditions and Cuſtoms,) made him ſo exceeding mad againſt all ſuch whoſe Doctrin or Practice was otherwiſe; could not bear with any alteration or turning out of his accuſtomed way, nor with any who did walk, profeſs or teach otherwiſe; therefore was he ſo vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in perſecuting of Chriſtians, and in his endeavors to hinder the ſpreading of the Goſpel, till Chriſt met with him, and convinced him to purpoſe of his miſtaken zeal. Another inſtance of this is noted by <hi>Daniel,</hi> in his days, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. When the King there had ſet up an Image, <hi>v.</hi> 1. and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated it, <hi>v.</hi> 3. and in the following verſes, proclaimed <hi>that all ſhould at ſuch times fall down and worſhip:</hi> And the <hi>Caldeans</hi> great zeal for this Idolatry put them upon accuſing <hi>Shadrach, Meſhach</hi> and <hi>Abednego,</hi> &amp;c. for not worſhiping this Image as the <hi>Caldeans</hi> did worſhip; this alſo ſet the King into a great rage too againſt them, (ſuch was his zeal alſo); yea, to ſuch a degree too, that when they had utterly denyed to worſhip the Image, he commanded the Furnace to be heat ſeventy times hotter, and they to be caſt in, which was executed <hi>v.</hi> 21. So hot was he for his Image-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, that the Non-complyers muſt die for it. Upon the like ground alſo did the Scribes and Phariſees quarrel with Chriſt and his Diſciples in thoſe days, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15. <hi>Why,</hi> ſay they there to Chriſt, <hi>do thy Diſciples tranſgreſs the Traditions of the the Elders? for they waſh not their hands when they eat Bread,</hi> v. 2. Their Heat and Fervor for their Religion and Traditions put them upon this Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling, tho Chriſt had told them, that they by their Traditions had made void the Law of God;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:41342:14"/> this Tradition and Cuſtom of theirs is ſet forth in <hi>Mark</hi> 7.3, 4. thus, <hi>That the Phariſees and the</hi> Jews <hi>except they waſh their hands oft, eat not, holding the Traditions of the Elders; and when they came from the Market, except they waſhed they would not eat; and many other things there be which they have received to hold, as the waſhing of Cups and Pots, Braſen-veſſels, and of Tables</hi> (or Beds). Their Heart engagedneſs to theſe Ways and Traditions received of their Father, made them quarrel at Chriſt and his Followers for not obſerving of them: So again, for not obſerving the Sabbath, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. they ſaid, <hi>Behold, thy Diſciples do that which is not lawful to do on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day,</hi> v. 2. And this put them upon endeavoring to enſnare Chriſt by queſtions, and take coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel againſt him how they might deſtroy him; they could not bear with ſuch who did not as they did in theſe matters in thoſe days. The Philoſophers were ſo addicted to their Idols, <hi>Act.</hi> 17. that they deſpiſed <hi>Paul</hi> and his Doctrin, and ſaid, <hi>v.</hi> 14. <hi>What will this babler ſay, he ſeemeth to be a ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter forth of ſtrange gods;</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 19, 20. they ſaid, <hi>May we know what this new Doctrin whereof thou ſpeakeſt is? For thou bringeſt certain things; we would know therefore what theſe things mean.</hi> Theſe could not bear with the preaching up the true God; they being worſhipers of Idols, the true God was a ſtrange God to them; and what <hi>Paul</hi> had preached were ſtrange things, becauſe contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to what they had been bred up in; and their zeal was ſo hot for their falſe Worſhip, that they deſpiſed and perſecuted ſuch as offered the true; they took <hi>Paul</hi> here and carryed him before the higheſt Court, where they put theſe queſtions to him: After the ſame manner did the <hi>Jews</hi> with <hi>Paul</hi> upon this ground too, <hi>Act.</hi> 18.11. He having before preached Jeſus Chriſt to them at <hi>Corinth, They here with one accord made an inſurrection againſt him, and brought him to the Judgment Seat, ſaying, This Fellow perſuadeth men to worſhip God contrary to the Law:</hi> Here now was the great ground of their Enmity and Violence againſt him; they could not bear to have Men worſhip God in any other way, than in that which they had uſually worſhiped according to the Law and their Traditions, nor bear with any Perſuaſions thereunto; ſuch was their blind zeal for that wherein they had been educated and uſed to. Their old received Cuſtoms were more valued by them than the Laws of God; tho God was then to be worſhiped otherwiſe, as Chriſt had hinted to them; and as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 24. there confeſſed before the Governor that he did, <hi>v.</hi> 14. in theſe words, <hi>After the way they call Hereſie, ſo worſhip I the God of my Fathers, believing all things written in the Law and the Prophets:</hi> But becauſe he did diſſent from their Traditions and Cuſtoms, and worſhiped not as they did, therefore called they his Way Hereſie; and they perſecuted him as in the beginning of the Chapter and before, altho it was according to what was written in the Law and the Prophets. So again, <hi>Act.</hi> 21. <hi>The</hi> Jews <hi>there,</hi> v. 27. <hi>ſtirred up the People, and laid hands on</hi> Paul, <hi>and</hi> v. 28. <hi>cryed out, this is the man who teacheth all men every where againſt the People, and the Law, and this Place:</hi> This was the great thing which moved them here; <hi>Paul</hi> had taught the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to worſhip God otherwiſe than according to the Ceremonies of the Law, the Cuſtoms and Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of the <hi>Jews,</hi> wherein they had been ſo long converſant; and this they could not bear with. The Admirers of <hi>Diana</hi> did ſo too, <hi>Act.</hi> 19. when the Silverſmith there had (tho upon another ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count,) inſinuated, that the Apoſtles did deſign by their Preaching, to diſgrace and render their Goddeſs <hi>Diana</hi> contemptible, <hi>v.</hi> 24, 25. and ſo on. Theſe Adorers of <hi>Diana</hi> were very wroth upon the hearing on't, and the whole City was filled with confuſion, crying up <hi>Diana;</hi> O they could not bear with any thing which they had apprehended to have any tendency to the leſſening of their ſo much admired <hi>Diana,</hi> which quickly put them into an unanſwerable uprore and violence againſt <hi>Pauls</hi> Companions, whom they had caught, <hi>v.</hi> 28. and ſo on, as the Town Clerk himſelf had told them, <hi>v.</hi> 37, 38. and ſo on. Thus the Scpipture hath taken notice of this Cauſe alſo of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity in the Breaſts of wicked Men, and of their perſecuting Spirit againſt the Saints in thoſe days.</p>
            <p n="7">7thly. There was yet a ſeventh cauſe or riſe of the Enmity and perſecuting Practices of theſe againſt the Saints, which thoſe divine Records hath ſet down in it; that was the privat Profit and Gain that ſome Men had by ſome Religion then profeſſed, or ſome other Way then in eſteem a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:41342:15"/> the People; which Gain being by Chriſt or the Apoſtles, preaching of the truth, abated, or in danger of being gone; they were ſet in a rage againſt the Truth, and againſt all thoſe who preached it, or believed and embraced it; they could not bear with the thoughts of their Gain be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken away; therefore did perſecute and endeavor to deſtroy the Apoſtles and others, and uſed all means to prevent the ſpreading of their Doctrins. This very thing put the Silverſmiths upon ſtirring up the People, who were the great Adorers of <hi>Diana, Act.</hi> 19. Not their zeal for <hi>Diana</hi> ſo much, as for their Profit: When <hi>Paul</hi> there had preached in <hi>Aſia,</hi> and turning People from the worſhiping of falſe gods; the Silverſmiths preſently apprehending that this would bring <hi>Diana</hi> their Goddeſs, into diſeſteem, that People would not worſhip her any more, and then farwell their Gain; which matter ſo troubled them, that 'tis ſaid thus there, <hi>v.</hi> 23. <hi>That there was no ſmall ſtir about this way;</hi> and in the next verſes, <hi>That</hi> Demetrius <hi>who made the Silver Shrines to</hi> Diana; <hi>brought no ſmall gain to the Craftsmen, whom he called together, and ſaid unto them, Ye know that by this craft we have our wealth;</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> hath ſaid, <hi>They be no gods which are made with hands; ſo that not only our craft is in danger, but</hi> Diana <hi>would be deſpiſed;</hi> which Saying proved ſufficient to beget an Enmity in the Breaſts of the Craftsmen againſt the Apoſtles and that Doctrin, and to ſet them upon perſecuting of them, as in the following verſes they did; for they very well knew; that if once the People did believe that the Religion and Worſhip they were found in were not right, <hi>Diana</hi> no Goddeſs; and that all their Zeal in and for that way, was no better than Vanity; Superſtition and Idolatry; then no body would imploy them to make Silver Shrines for <hi>Diana</hi> any more, and conſequently they muſt take leave of their old Gain; this now ſet them into ſuch a flame of Envy and Violence againſt the Apoſtles and their Preaching. From the very ſame cauſe were the Maſters of the Damſel, who was poſſeſſed with the Spirit of Divination ſtirred up againſt <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Sylas,</hi> and did perſecute them, <hi>Act.</hi> 16.16. 'tis there ſaid, <hi>That a certain Damſel poſſeſſed with a Spirit of Divination met us, who brought her maſter much gain by ſouthſaying, whom</hi> Paul, in <hi>v.</hi> 18. <hi>caſt out;</hi> upon which <hi>her maſters,</hi> in the next verſes, <hi>caught</hi> Paul <hi>and</hi> Sylas, <hi>and drew them unto the Rulers unto the Magiſtrates, ſaying, Theſe being</hi> Jews <hi>do exceedingly trouble our City and teach Cuſtoms,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Upon which the multitude roſe up againſt them, and the Magiſtrates commanded them to be beaten,</hi> which they did, <hi>and put them into Priſon.</hi> The main cauſe of all theſe Accuſations and Complaints againſt them, and of their Impriſonment and Beating, was only the loſs of that Gain the Damſel had brought her Maſters; as 'tis expreſly ſaid, <hi>v.</hi> 19. in theſe words, <hi>And when her maſters ſaw that the hope of their gain was gone, they caught</hi> Paul, &amp;c. Thus hath the Scripture alſo taken notice of this cauſe too, why ſome in thoſe Ages of the World, did hate and perſecute the Saints.</p>
            <p n="8">8thly. Yet further, theſe divine Records hath taken notice of an eighth cauſe or ſpring from whence ill Mens Spirits were moved againſt the good, or from whence many were engaged in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting and deſtroying of them; that was from a fear of, or deſire to pleaſe and gratifie others; ſome great Men, or Men of Power, who were themſelves full of Envy and Malice againſt the Saints, and did perſecute them; and thereby to ſecure to themſelves the good opinion of thoſe ſtill, tho o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe againſt their own judgments and inclinations, and it may be againſt convictions too, that in ſo doing they did not well; as the Scripture ſpeaks it was in Chriſts time, <hi>John</hi> 12.42. Some great ones there did believe on Chriſt; but 'tis expreſly ſaid, <hi>That becauſe of the Phariſees they did not confeſs him, leſt they ſhould have been put out of the Synagogue;</hi> and the reaſon in the next verſe, is given for it further; <hi>For</hi> ('tis ſaid,) <hi>they loved the praiſe of Men more than the praiſe of God:</hi> And doubtleſs, theſe who would not looſe the praiſe of Men, did ſit and judge with their Fellow Rulers, when they perſecute Chriſt and his Followers, whatever their own thoughts on't were; their deſire to abide in the good opinion of the Great Ones, and their fear of being frowned upon by them, put them upon thus doing againſt ſuch of whom they had good thoughts: And as the Elders and Nobles dwelling in the City where <hi>Naboth</hi> lived, did obey the wicked command of <hi>Jezebel,</hi> in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habs</hi> name, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21. They feared no doubt, the diſpleaſing or looſing the Favor of <hi>Jezebel</hi> or
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:41342:15"/> 
               <hi>Ahab;</hi> therefore executed that wicked Command againſt innocent <hi>Naboth,</hi> as in <hi>v.</hi> 8, 9. and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing verſes; <hi>Jezebel there writes in the Kings name and under his ſeal, and ſent it to theſe Nobles and Elders, that they ſhould proclaim a Fast, ſet</hi> Naboth <hi>on high, and ſet two witneſſes, Sons of</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lial <hi>before him, ſaying, Thou didſt blaſpheme God and the King; and then to carry him out and ſtone him,</hi> which the Elders and Nobles readily did, rather than they would run the hazard of falling in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the King or Queens disfavor; altho they knew in ſo doing, they did ſhed innocent Blood moſt unjuſtly, under the notion of a judicial Proceeding, <hi>v.</hi> 12, 13. and no other cauſe of their execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this wicked Commandment can be aſſigned with any probability. So <hi>Herod</hi> in his days, from this very Root did deal ſo with <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt, Mat.</hi> 14. <hi>He</hi> v. 10. <hi>ſent and beheaded</hi> John <hi>the</hi> Baptiſt <hi>in Priſon;</hi> and the Evangeliſt there in the former verſes, give this as the cauſe, or that which put him upon ſo doing; he having formerly promiſed to the Daughter of <hi>Herodias, that ſhe ſhould have whatſoever ſhe ſhould have asked,</hi> v. 7. <hi>and ſhe</hi> v. 8. <hi>asking</hi> Johns <hi>head;</hi> 'tis expreſly ſaid <hi>v.</hi> 9. <hi>That the King was very ſorry: nevertheleſs, for the Oaths ſake and them who ſat at meat with him, he commanded it to be done:</hi> Here <hi>Herods</hi> unwillingneſs to diſpleaſe his Company, took away <hi>Johns</hi> life; that did influence him here to do, what otherwiſe he would not have done. And again, it is ſaid of <hi>Herod, Act.</hi> 12.1. <hi>That he ſtretched forth his hand to vex certain of the Church,</hi> v. 2. <hi>He killed</hi> James <hi>with the ſword; and</hi> v. 3. <hi>becauſe he ſaw it pleaſed the</hi> Jews, <hi>he proceeded further to take</hi> Peter <hi>alſo;</hi> To perſecute the Church was a matter ſo light to him, that he could do it upon ſo ſmall a motive as the pleaſing of the <hi>Jews,</hi> who were fixed in their Enmity againſt Chriſt, his Diſciples and Doctrin before, as he well knew. In like manner did <hi>Felix</hi> with <hi>Paul</hi> upon the fame motive, <hi>Act.</hi> 24.26, 27. <hi>Having ſent for</hi> Paul <hi>often;</hi> and when another Governor came in <hi>Felix</hi> room, he left <hi>Paul</hi> bound, (tho he knew him to be innocent,) upon this ground only, as 'tis expreſly ſaid, <hi>That</hi> Felix <hi>willing to ſhew the</hi> Jews <hi>a pleaſure, left</hi> Paul <hi>bound;</hi> The pleaſing of the perſecuting <hi>Jews,</hi> was of ſufficient force to perſuade him to leave <hi>Paul</hi> bound. So is it ſaid of <hi>Feſtus</hi> himſelf, <hi>Act.</hi> 25. <hi>Paul</hi> having pleaded his own Innocency before him, <hi>Feſtus</hi> to gratifie the deſire of the <hi>Jews,</hi> (who had a deſign to have killed <hi>Paul</hi> in the way,) perſuadeth <hi>Paul</hi> not to have ſtood to his Appeal, but to go to <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> deſire and deſign is expreſſed in <hi>v.</hi> 2, &amp; 3. in theſe words, <hi>The High Prieſt and the Chief of the</hi> Jews <hi>informed him againſt</hi> Paul, <hi>and deſired favor againſt him, that he would ſend for him to</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>laying wait in the way to kill him;</hi> upon which <hi>Feſtus</hi> v. 9 (moved thereto only upon this account, that he thereby might pleaſe the <hi>Jews,</hi>) would have expoſed <hi>Paul</hi> to their intended Violence, as 'tis expreſſed there in theſe words, <hi>But</hi> Feſtus <hi>willing to do the</hi> Jews <hi>a pleaſure, anſwered</hi> Paul <hi>and ſaid, Wilt thou go up unto</hi> Jeruſalem. <hi>Pilate</hi> alſo under the ſame Temptation, (being willing to keep the favor of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and loath to be accout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Diſloyal; the <hi>Jews</hi> having urged that Argument,) did deliver up Chriſt to be Crucified, as is fully expreſſed <hi>John</hi> 19. for he had acknowledged Chriſts innocency often, as in <hi>Chap.</hi> 18. v. 38. in theſe words, <hi>I find in him no fault at all;</hi> and in Chap. 19. <hi>v.</hi> 4. <hi>Behold, I bring him forth to you, that ye may know that I find no fault in him;</hi> the ſame words again he ſaid to them, <hi>Yea, and</hi> v. 12. <hi>he ſought to releaſe him; But the</hi> Jews <hi>then</hi> in the next words, <hi>crying out, if thou let this man go thou art not</hi> Caeſars <hi>friend;</hi> which when <hi>Pilate</hi> had heard, their clamour prevailed: Here was he touched when nothing elſe would prevail by Argument of force, to cauſe him to deliver up Jeſus to be Crucified; this was, he either for fear of looſing <hi>Caeſars</hi> favor, being thought no Friend of his, or to pleaſe the <hi>Jews,</hi> did that which was otherwiſe againſt his own judgment and inclination; for in <hi>Mark</hi> 15.15. 'tis ſaid, <hi>That he did it to pleaſe the multitude;</hi> ſo that both ſeemed to be upon his Heart. Thus hath the Scripture alſo taken notice, that fear of Flattery was often the main cauſe which put many Perſons upon the unjuſt and cruel Perſecuting of innocent and good Men, and to aſſiſt others therein, when nothing elſe would have influenced to ſuch Doings.</p>
            <p>In the fourth and laſt place, the Scripture is not ſilent neither, in ſetting forth the deſperateneſs of ſuch a Spirit of Enmity, and of ſuch perſecuting Practices in thoſe wicked Men, in thoſe Ages of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:41342:16"/> the World. Firſt, In that it ſheweth, that God himſelf and Chriſt did take themſelves to be concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in all that which was done againſt his People: And Secondly, It declared the many direful Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings againſt ſuch Perſecutors; as alſo the ſad Effects and Conſequents of ſuch Doings. And Firſt, It ſets forth how much God and Chriſt reaſons themſelves concerned therewith, as he was for his People under the burthen laid upon them in <hi>Egypt,</hi> Exod. 3. <hi>God ſaid,</hi> v. 7. <hi>I have ſurely ſeen the affliction of my people which are in</hi> Egypt; <hi>and I have heard their cry, by reaſon of their Task maſters: for I know their ſorrow;</hi> and in the next verſe, <hi>I am come down to deliver them;</hi> of which God told <hi>Moſes</hi> again, <hi>v.</hi> 9. Here is obſerved what notice God took on't, and how he was concerned about it. So again, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105. 'tis ſaid of <hi>Iſrael</hi> there by the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> v. 13, 14, 15. <hi>That when they went from one nation to another,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>he ſuffered no man to do them wrong; yea, he reproved Kings for their ſakes, ſaying, Touch not my Anointed, and do my Prophets no harm. Iſaiah</hi> records theſe words, <hi>Chap.</hi> 63.8, 9. <hi>He was their Saviour: in all their afflictions he was afflicted, and the Angel of his preſence ſaved them: in his love and in his pity he redeemed them,</hi> &amp;c. Here were great Expreſſions of his care and concernedneſs for them. God himſelf by the Prophet <hi>Zachariah</hi> ſpake thus concerning them, <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. v. 8. <hi>He who toucheth you, toucheth the Apple of mine eye;</hi> and in <hi>v.</hi> 9. he ſaith of their Enemies, <hi>Behold, I will ſhake mine hand upon them,</hi> &amp;c. So did Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf declare his concernedneſs for the Church, when <hi>Saul</hi> had perſecuted them, <hi>Act.</hi> 9.1, 2, 3. <hi>Chriſt met him in the way;</hi> and in the next verſes uttered theſe words, <hi>Saul, Saul, why perſecuteſt thou me? Who art thou, ſaid</hi> Saul! <hi>I am</hi> Jeſus <hi>whom thou perſecuteſt; it is hard for thee to kick a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the pricks:</hi> Here Chriſt evidenced himſelf to be neerly concerned for his Saints; and alſo he hinted to <hi>Saul</hi> the danger of perſecuting too, <hi>It is hard for thee to kick againſt the pricks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then Secondly, The Scripture Records, the many direful Threatnings againſt ſuch Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors in thoſe days, and declared the many ſad Effects and Conſequents of ſuch doing in thoſe Ages of the World. In the general, God ſaid, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. <hi>v.</hi> 43. <hi>That he will revenge the blood of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and will render vengeance to the adverſaries:</hi> And again, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7.13. <hi>He hath ordained his arrows againſt the Perſecutors.</hi> Yea, thus ſpake he to his People <hi>Iſrael</hi> in particular, by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> Chap. 10. <hi>O my people,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>be not afraid of the</hi> Aſſyrians, <hi>he ſhall ſmite thee with a rod,</hi> v. 24. and in <hi>v.</hi> 25, &amp; 26. <hi>For yet a little while and the indignation ſhall ceaſe, and mine an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, in their deſtruction; and the Lord of hoſts ſhall ſtir up a ſcourge for him, according to the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of</hi> Midian: Yea, and tho their ſtout Hearts would not take notice of Gods Hand lifted up againſt them, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26. yet God ſaid there, <hi>That they ſhould ſee and be aſhamed for their envy at the people,</hi> (or towards my people); <hi>yea,</hi> (ſaid he there,) <hi>the fire of thine enemies ſhall devour them,</hi> v. 11. Again, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51. <hi>I have taken out of thine hand the cup of trembling, the dregs of the cup of my fury; thou ſhalt no more drink it again, but I will put it into the hands of them who afflict thee, who ſaid to thy ſoul, bow down that we may go over,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>v.</hi> 22, 23. Here God, tho he did permit his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Enemies ſometimes to lay the Rod on his, yet the Dregs of the Cup the Enemies, Perſecuters themſelves are threatned to drink; with which God threatned ſeveral Nations, who had been his Peopls. <hi>Iſraels</hi> great Enemies and Oppreſſors, for their inſolent inſulting over them, and for all their cruel and ſevere Dealings with them, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 25. <hi>The</hi> Amonites <hi>for their ſaying Aha, Aha, againſt Gods Sanctuary when it was profaned, and againſt the land of</hi> Iſrael <hi>when it was deſolate, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the houſe of</hi> Judah <hi>when they went into captivity,</hi> v. 3. and in the next verſes, there are Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings denounced againſt them for this further, and for that <hi>That they had claped their hands and rejoyced in heart, with all their deſpight againſt the Land of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>v.</hi> 6. and in the following verſes Threatnings are denounced againſt them, and againſt <hi>Moab</hi> too in the 8, 9, and following verſes; and <hi>v.</hi> 12. 'tis ſaid from the Lord, <hi>That becauſe</hi> Edom <hi>hath dealt againſt the houſe of</hi> Judah <hi>by tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vengeance, and hath greatly offended and revenged himſelf upon them; therefore did God threaten them ſorely</hi> in the next verſes; and again, in <hi>v.</hi> 15. 'tis ſaid of the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> thus, <hi>Becauſe they dealt by revenge, and have taken vengeance with a deſpightful heart, to deſtroy for the old hatred;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41342:16"/> therefore thus ſaith the Lord, I will ſtretch forth my hand,</hi> &amp;c. in the next verſes. God alſo threatens <hi>Titus</hi> for the lifting up her ſelf againſt <hi>Iſrael;</hi> ſee it at large, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 26. and in Chap. 35. God by the Prophet there ſaith to Mount <hi>Seir</hi> thus, <hi>I am againſt thee, and I will ſtretch out mine hand againſt thee, and I will make thee moſt deſolate,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>v.</hi> 1, 2, 3, 4. and in <hi>v.</hi> 5. he declares the cauſe in theſe words, <hi>Becauſe thou haſt a perpetual hatred, and haſt ſhed the blood of the Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>by the force of the ſword, and in the time of their calamity,</hi> &amp;c. and in the next verſes he ſaith, <hi>I will prepare thee to blood, and blood ſhall purſue thee,</hi> &amp;c. So did God threaten the Heathen in general for the ſame cauſe, in Chap. 36. at the beginning; and in <hi>Zephan,</hi> Chap. 2. did he threaten <hi>Moab</hi> and <hi>Ammon</hi> upon this account, <hi>v.</hi> 8. <hi>I have heard the reproach of</hi> Moab, (ſaid he,) <hi>and the revilings of the Children of</hi> Ammon, <hi>whereby they have reproached my people, and magnified themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their borders: therefore as I live, ſaith the Lord</hi> there, <hi>v.</hi> 9. and ſo on, <hi>Moab ſhall as</hi> Sodom, &amp;c. Nay, God threatned <hi>the Heads of</hi> Jacob <hi>and Princes of the houſe of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>for their hating of the good and loving of the evil,</hi> and (as the natural conſequent thereof,) their hurting and perſecuting of his People, <hi>Micah</hi> 3.1, 2, 3, 4. And again he threatens <hi>Edom,</hi> in <hi>Obadiah, v.</hi> 9, &amp; 10. for this cauſe too, in theſe words, <hi>And thy mighty men, O</hi> Teman, <hi>ſhall be diſmayed, to the end that every one of the mount of</hi> Eſau <hi>may be cut off by ſlaughter: for thy violence againſt thy Brother</hi> Jacob, <hi>ſhame ſhall cover thee, and thou ſhalt be cut off for ever:</hi> Thus did God in thoſe days, take notice of the abuſes done to his, and did threaten their Perſecutors. Yea further, in the days of the New Teſtament too, doth the Holy Ghoſt take ſpecial notice of theſe things; Chriſt himſelf pronounced a woe in general to ſuch who ſhould offend his, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. ſaid he there, <hi>Whoſoever ſhall offend one of theſe little ones which believe in me, it were better for him that a millſtone were hanged about his neck, and that he were drowned in the depth of the Sea,</hi> v. 6. and in <hi>v.</hi> 7. he adds <hi>a woe to the world becauſe of offences,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and woe to the man by whom they come;</hi> this he ſpake in general, but more particular to the <hi>Jews:</hi> He in <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.29, 30. pronounced Woes againſt them upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, and ſpake dreadfully to them, <hi>v.</hi> 34, &amp; 37. in theſe words, <hi>I ſend you Prophets,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and ſome of them ye ſhall kill and crucifie; and ſome of them ſhall you ſcourge in your Synagogues, and perſecute them from City to City: That upon you may come, all the righteous blood ſhed upon the Earth, from righteous</hi> Abel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> According to which the Apoſtle ſpake, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. of the <hi>Jews,</hi> he having ſaid to the <hi>Theſſalonians, v.</hi> 14. <hi>That they alſo had ſuffered like things of their Countrymen, as they have of the</hi> Jews; he <hi>v.</hi> 15. ſaid of them in theſe words, <hi>Who killed the Lord Jeſus and their own Prophets, and have perſecuted us; and they pleaſe not God, and are contrary to all men; forbidding us to ſpeak to the Gentiles, that they might be ſaved:</hi> Here were they highly engaged in a perſecut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Spirit, and of oppoſition of the Goſpel of Salvation. But what ſaith the Holy Ghoſt in the next words, concerning the Conſequents thereof; <hi>To fill up their ſin alway</hi> (ſaith he,) <hi>for the wrath is come upon them to the uttermoſt.</hi> And leaſt any Man ſhould flatter himſelf with vain hopes of Eſcaping, tho he ſhould have perſiſted in ſuch a Spirit and Practice; Chriſt himſelf hath poſſitive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſerted, that God will avenge it, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.7, 8. in theſe words, <hi>Shall not God avenge his own elect, who cry day and night unto him,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I tell you, that he will avenge them ſpeedily:</hi> Here or hereafter, vengeanc will overtake the Enemies and Perſecutors of his Elect; and that it is but juſt in God ſo to do, the Apoſtle intimates 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.6, 7. and ſo on in theſe words, <hi>Seeing it is a righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous thing with God, to recompence tribulation to them who trouble you, and to you who are troubled reſt, when the Lord Jeſus ſhall be revealed,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>to take vengeance on them who know not God,</hi> &amp;c. v. 9. Their puniſhment is ſaid to be then their everlaſting deſtruction, from the Preſence of the Lord and the Glory of his Power: And the righteouſneſs of God is proclaimed in his executing this vengeance on them, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16. <hi>v.</hi> 5, 6. in theſe words, <hi>Thou art righteous, O Lord,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>becauſe thou haſt judged thus: for they have ſhed the blood of Saints and Prophets, and thou haſt given them blood to drink, for they are worthy.</hi> The Scripture hath taken notice, that ſometimes God did exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute threatned Judgments upon ſuch in this World; ſo did he with all the Countrys before threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:41342:17"/> for their hatred againſt, and vengeance and cruelty they took and exerciſed upon his People <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and <hi>Haman</hi> himſelf met with the ſame evil he had deſigned to have executed upon <hi>Mordicai.</hi> And ſome times 'tis reſerved to be puniſhed in the World to come, and ſhall remain upon them for ever; of which Judgments unavoidably to come upon them, that envious Spirit they were found in, was a full evidence, as the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.28. to the perſecuted Saints in that day, by way of comfort to them, in theſe words, <hi>And in nothing terrified by your Adverſaries, which is to them an evident token of perdition, and to you of ſalvation, and that of God:</hi> And to which alſo Chriſt ſpake home unto the <hi>Jews, Mat.</hi> 25. ſpeaking there, <hi>v.</hi> 31. and ſo on, <hi>of his coming to judge the world;</hi> he <hi>v.</hi> 41, 42, and ſo on, ſaith, <hi>Then ſhall the King ſay unto them on the left hand, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from me ye curſed into everlaſting fire prepared for the Devil and his Angels; for I was an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary and ye gave me no meat, I was thirſty and ye gave me no drink, I was a ſtranger and ye took me not in, naked and ye cloathed me not, ſick and in priſon and ye viſited me not;</hi> and he explains his meaning to them in <hi>v.</hi> 45. <hi>In as much</hi> (ſaith he,) <hi>as ye did it not to one of the leaſt of theſe, ye did it not to me;</hi> and this direful Word followeth in <hi>v.</hi> 46. <hi>Theſe ſhall go away into everlaſting puniſhment;</hi> whence they might have eaſily inferred, that if it ſhould be ſo ſad with thoſe who gave not Meat, Cloathed not, gave not Drink, viſited not in Priſons in Sickneſs; how much more ſad would the Condition of ſuch be who took away their Meat and Drink, made them Poor and Naked, caſt them into Priſon, were inſtrumental to make them Sick, yea, and take away their Lives too? If a Woe be pronounced againſt them who are at eaſe in <hi>Zion,</hi> and not grieved for the Affliction of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> as in <hi>Amos</hi> 6.1, 2, 3. and ſo on, what might thoſe expect who were the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicters of <hi>Joſeph?</hi> It was no light thing when God ſhould come to avenge; for much the Apoſtle did give them to know in thoſe days, when he had affirmed <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.30. theſe words as that which God had ſaid, <hi>Vengeance belong to me, ſaith the Lord, and I will repay it,</hi> &amp;c. He ſubjoins this in the next verſe, <hi>It is a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the living God.</hi> Therefore God himſelf by the Prophet <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 2. After he had been Propheſying of the Rage of Princes and People againſt the Lord and his Anointed; and had ſet forth their Vanity and the ineffectualneſs of their Attempts againſt him, in the beginning of the <hi>Pſalm;</hi> he <hi>v.</hi> 10, 11, 12. adviſeth them to ſubmit, becauſe of the ſad Conſequents of their perſiſting in their Rage, in theſe words, <hi>Be wiſe now there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, O ye Kings, be inſtructed ye Judges of the Earth; ſerve the Lord with fear, and rejoyce with trembling; kiſs the Son leſt he be angry, and ye periſh from the way, when his wrath is kindled but a little,</hi> &amp;c. What dreadful Judgments hath befallen the <hi>Jews,</hi> ſince they in their rage againſt Chriſt, utttered theſe words, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.25. <hi>His blood be upon us and our Children!</hi> Thus do theſe divine Records eſpecially note the great and ſeated Enmity which was in the Hearts of wicked Men in thoſe days of the World, againſt good Men and Things; and the breakings out thereof in the ſeveral Ways they then took, to prevent the increaſe of them and it; together with the Cauſes or ſeveral Grounds from when that Spirit in thoſe days did ariſe and took life; as alſo the dreadful Caſe of ſuch, the ſad Conſequents of being found in ſuch a Spirit and Practices.</p>
            <p>And are not theſe things written (as are other things,) in the Scriptures of old, <hi>for the admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe upon whom the ends of the world are come?</hi> And doth it not concern all Men to inſtruct themſelves therein, in order to their own eſcape from the Errors of theſe, and ſo ſave themſelves from the direful Conſequents and Effects depending upon them?</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:41342:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
